<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine sermons preached of late at Ciceter, in the countie of Glocester vpon a portion of the first chapter of the Epistle of Iames: wherein the two seueral states, of the riche and poore man are compared and examined, the differences in quality, and duety betwixt them shewed, both directed to such Christian parts and offices, as the sufficiencie of the one may, and ought to performe, and the wants of the other do necessarily require. Penned at the earnest requests of diuers well affected inhabitantes of the place: and now published as wel for the vse of others, as for the further profit of that particular congregation. By Philip Iones, preacher of the word of God in the same towne. Allowed by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Jones, Philip, fl. 1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1384:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine sermons preached of late at Ciceter, in the countie of Glocester vpon a portion of the first chapter of the Epistle of Iames: wherein the two seueral states, of the riche and poore man are compared and examined, the differences in quality, and duety betwixt them shewed, both directed to such Christian parts and offices, as the sufficiencie of the one may, and ought to performe, and the wants of the other do necessarily require. Penned at the earnest requests of diuers well affected inhabitantes of the place: and now published as wel for the vse of others, as for the further profit of that particular congregation. By Philip Iones, preacher of the word of God in the same towne. Allowed by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Philip, fl. 1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[140] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. D[awson] for Thomas Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi A-G H⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE Sermons preached of late at Ciceter, in the countie of Gloceſter, vpon a portion of the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle of Iames: wherein the two ſeueral ſtates, of the riche and poore man are compared and examined, the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in quality, and duety betwixt them ſhewed, both directed to ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian parts and offices, as the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of the one may, and ought to performe, and the wants of the other do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily require.</p>
            <p>Penned at the earneſt requeſts of diuers <hi>well affected Inhabitantes of the place: and now publiſhed as well for the vſe of others, as for the further profit of that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Philip Iones,</hi> Preacher of the word of God in the ſame Towne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Allowed by authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by T. D. for <hi>Thomas Butter</hi> 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the right Reuerend Father in God, <hi>Iohn,</hi> nowe Biſhoppe of <hi>Gloceſter, and Commendatarie of Briſtow, Philip Iones</hi> wiſheth the increaſe of all good graces fit for the diſcharge, and anſwering of ſo great a calling in this life and in the next, the fruition of thoſe ioyes, which are euerlaſting in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>AVL that choſen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell vnto God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.15.</note> being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument or miniſter, for, the bearing of his name, before the Gentiles, and kings, &amp; the children of Iſrael, hauing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the handes of many keepers, Centurions, Souldiers, high prieſts, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, at laſt appeared in <hi>Ceſarea</hi> before <hi>Agrippa</hi> the king, who beeing deſirous to heare him and his cauſe, &amp; hauing for that purpoſe giuen him lawful libertie to ſpeake for him ſelfe, he thought and pronounced
<pb facs="tcp:20078:3"/>
him ſelfe happie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.2.3.</note> in that hee was called and permitted to anſwere before him of all the thinges whereof hee was accuſed of the Iewes, chiefly, becauſe hee had knowledge of all cuſtomes and queſtions which were then amongſt them. In like manner I at this time (right Reuerend) cannot but take my ſelfe if not in the ſame degree happie, yet in ſome proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortunate, in meeting with this preſent opportunitie for the vſe of free ſpeech to, and before you, not in the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and queſtions of the Iewes, but in the thinges that concerne a better ſtate and gouernment ſeene, and exerciſed ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For I eſteeme it no ſmall adiument, or furtherance of an honeſt cauſe, to haue ſuch a Iudge of the controuerſie as both in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is willing to heare, &amp; in iudgement able to determine according to reaſon &amp; equity: although at this time it is not my intention, to ſollicite you as a Iudge in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, but to purchaſe you as a Patrone to a ſchollers work: litle I confes in quantity, &amp; far from any exact or exquiſite thing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you reſpect the phraſe &amp; ſtile, or the maner of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling thorowout the whole tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate: by reaſon wherof, I coulde fully haue
<pb facs="tcp:20078:3"/>
ſatisfied my ſelf, either in the cloſe reſeruing therof amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g my papers, or otherwiſe in the priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating of the ſame with my friends: but being preſſed with the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of many good brethren, who being preſent at the preaching, haue made report of the fruit &amp; benefit they therby reaped, &amp; therefore would take no anſwere, but the graunt of a publike vſe of the ſame, for their further comfort, and the profit of others, I coulde not in conſcience or curteſie, denie ſo reaſonable a requeſt proceeding from ſuch Chriſtian &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable minds. And hauing at the laſt, for their contentment in this one part (though leauing them diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, for the reſt,) yeelded to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of reaſons, wherewith they vrged me, I haue taken this courſe, and made this choiſe in the publiſhing to vſe your Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend name, and patronage for the ſame. VVherunto beſides ſundrie effectuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues inducing me, (which for ſome reſpects I here ſuppreſſe) one is of good conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, meete in this place to bee introduced, and ſpecified: and that is, an earneſt deſire wherewith I haue for a ſeaſon trauailed, to haue you thorowly acquaynted with
<pb facs="tcp:20078:4"/>
the ſtate, and trueth of certaine actions of mine, which by reaſon of the practiſes of ſuche aduerſaries,<note place="margin">Ezra. 4.1.</note> as <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin</hi> ſometimes had, in a matter not muche different in nature though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in circumſtance, are ſo farre from beeing entertayned with lawfull fauour, as that they are proſecuted with extreeme diſpleaſure vnder you, yea and by you, (as of late in your heate and pasſions openly appeared) to the great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the common enemie, and no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſcomfort of manie that profeſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and diſcreetely. I craue pardon if anie ſyllable ſounding to offence, bee in my wordes to your ſelfe or others towards whom my meaning perhappes may ſeeme to reache: for, I carrie no purpoſe to rippe vp, particular matters or to make the name of any man odious by complaint, but onely a care, and conſcience to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne a good cauſe, to deliuer the trueth of thinges, and to preſerue from wracke a Chriſtian account, and reputation, which according to <hi>Salomon</hi> maketh fatte the bones.<note place="margin">Prou. 15.30</note> VVhich thinges I fynde my ſelfe animated in this ſorte (or otherwiſe if
<pb facs="tcp:20078:4"/>
occaſion bee offered) to vndertake vppon this ſurmiſe, that to your ſelfe, (I meane your ſelfe, ſimplie conſidered, and not by others inchaunted) there cannot be a thing of more prompt acceptance then an honeſt meane vſed to remoue ſuch vnkinde and cauſeleſſe opinions, as vpon priuie ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue beene (too eaſily) conceiued, and to ſcatter ſuch miſtes of accuſations, as by the inuentions of malignant ſpirits, haue beene plotted, &amp; preferred againſt my tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate courſe. I ſpeak nothing but that which is common in the knowledge of the world,<note place="margin">Acts 26.26.</note> as not don in a corner: the dealings of ſome men (I will not ſay monſters, being ſuch ſo many ſo impudent, ſo malitious, &amp; ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt vs, as that a way to preuent their miſchiefes, and a time to breath our ſelues are hardly recouered, from their ordinarie vexations. Whereunto when I adde in my priuate conſideration, the immoderate and fierce proceedings of your ſelf, your courts, and officers, by interrupting the vſe of my miniſtery, and ſtretching the armes of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to the vttermoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I may not ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond law, reaſon, and chriſtian conſcience) to the increaſe of my diſquietinges, and the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:5"/>
full meaſure of my moleſtations, I ſee ſmall cauſe in common ſenſe, of taking any heart or ſpirite to fulfill my courſe, and to growe on in that ſpirituall worke, whereof a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of great hope is already made, and a foundation layd amongſt them, who at this preſent doe inioy the benefite of my attendance: when as thoſe who after a ſort naturally (by the communitie of office) ſhold lend their ſhoulders &amp; ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to beare of the blowes, and iniuries of hypocrites &amp; the broode of vipers, doe contrary to the courſe of nature, and duetie, ioyne (as it is feared) with them, to ſtrengthen their practiſes, and to giue more life to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, for the vtter ſpoyle &amp; ouerthrowe of many good &amp; ſinguler poſſibilities, which thing hath made me of this opinion, that either you haue egregiouſly forgotten (my reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to your place &amp; perſon premiſed) or that you do wittingly neglect the aduiſe, or rather charge of the moſt reuerend, &amp; honorable, the Archbiſhoppe of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for dutie &amp; honors ſake, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of many his ſpeciall fauors towards my ſelfe I here ree<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mber) ſent &amp; directed to you by letter, to doe nothing, that might te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to my diſcourage or troble, bearing my
<pb facs="tcp:20078:5"/>
ſelf in that lawful, &amp; anſwerable ſort wherin I haue alwayes ſquared, &amp; meaſured the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of my miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; whether I haue done ſo or not, I referre the iudgement to the teſtimonies of all indifferent perſons not ſurpriſed with malice towards vs, nor tranſported with parciallitie to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea to your ſelf, &amp; your own ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, when the time ſhal come, and occaſion ſhal yeeld it ſelf, to impart with you the true, &amp; perfect knowledge, of all late accidentes, touching both ſides, and cauſes. In the meane time I conceiue hope of this effect, that vpon the peruſing of this parte of my poore daily labors, which with all ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and regard of duetie I preſent you, your ſelfe of your wiſedome will diſcerne, what great &amp; manifeſt vntruth the aduerſaries reportes doe carry with them, which ſpare not to charge my indeuors, with bitter inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues againſt perſons, and ſeditious ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt authoritie, and the preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie &amp; gouernment of our church eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. <hi>Ab vno diſce omnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aenead. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> by this one you may iudge of al my trauels: for I my ſelfe in the feare of God do proteſt, &amp; the common audience of our aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies, can &amp; wil witnes, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner &amp; method, vſed and to be ſeen
<pb facs="tcp:20078:6"/>
herein, hath beene, and is the true forme of my dayly practiſe and performance of duetie. And I am not in the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and neceſſarie adiunctes of my profeſſion ſo much to ſeeke, but that I know according to the minde of a worthy and famous Prelate of this our age,<note place="margin">Ioh. Iuellus. in lib. de vit. Iuel.</note> and countrey (whoſe name, and memorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs is better then any ſweete, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent oyntment as the wiſe man ſpeaketh) that the preaching of the Goſpell ſtandeth not in an idle and vnfruitfull diſcourſing of rites,<note place="margin">Eccles 7.3.</note> and ceremonies, but in a ſound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery, and application of doctrine to the conſcience of a Chriſtian to worke faith, and repentance in the hearers: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I doubte not but that howſoeuer hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite hath curried fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with his maiſter, by diſcloſing <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.9.</note> and accuſing <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tub,</hi> I meane howſoeuer ſome whiſperers haue preuayled with your good nature (for what thing by crafte is ſooner abuſed?) wreſting the ſame to a hard conceit, and miſconſtruction of vs, and our actions, yet now vpon this iuſt, and reaſonable apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for our ſelues, your grauitie will bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:6"/>
and carry <hi>Alexanders</hi> two eares,<note place="margin">Bruſon. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> one alwayes ſtopt, and reſerued for the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſo ſhall colours be quickly diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from cauſes, and the truth of things ſhalbe receiued, and not the informations of thoſe men credited, which carry in their boſomes large conſciences to diſpence with any report be it neuer ſo adulterate, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my preiudice. And as I doubt not of this, ſo I miſtruſt not the iſſue of a further thing, to wit: that although <hi>Agrippa,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Pauls notable and true decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,<note place="margin">Acts. 26.31.32.</note> and the euident immerit of his bondes departed from the common hall, doing nothing in his matter, ſpeaking well of him, and his innocencie but not deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him according to iuſtice and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a king, yet your reuerend diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hauing diſcouered the pretences of the aduerſarie, and hauing viewed with a good eye the vprightnes of our cauſe, will, not in regard of vs, but of the matter directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue to the honour of God, and the health of many ſoules, execute with a good conſcience, that iudiciall preſcription, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by the Lorde himſefe to <hi>Moſes,</hi> not as pertinent to that time, and his policie
<pb facs="tcp:20078:7"/>
onely,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note> but perpetuall for all ages, thou ſhalt not agree in a controuerſie, to decline after many and ouerthrowe the truth. And in ſo doing I hope the time ſhall come, wherein as in the dayes of <hi>Salomon</hi> a man may dwell without feare vnder his vine,<note place="margin">1. Kings 4.25.</note> and figtree, from Dan euen to Beerſheba: and thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hope for my ſupport I reſt for this preſent, commending my ſelf to your good opinion, and ſpeech, and my poore labor to your protection: requeſting vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight, rather your partiall, then equall iudgment, becauſe of the imperfections ſcattered in the ſame: the graunt whereof I ſhall take and repute, not onely as a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent recompence and ſatiſfaction for this paines, but a ſpurre and prouocation alſo in time by the will of God, to ſhadowe vnder the breadth of your winges, matters of more ſubſtance, and greater perfection, The God and father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, the ſheepehearde, and Biſhoppe of our ſoules, who hath furniſhed you with many good graces, multiplie the ſame in you with all things neceſſarie for your roome, and place that God by you in al your actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may be glorified, the truth of
<pb facs="tcp:20078:7"/>
his worde and myſteries ratified, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſers thereof cheriſhed and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the idle and ignorant miniſters (the bane of our Church) reformed, and your ſelfe in the ende bleſſed with endleſſe feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie. London. May the 17. 1588.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Lordes vnworthy ſeruant, <hi>and your ſuppliant, prepared for all godly commaundements and duties. PHILIP IONES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:8"/>
            <head>The text.</head>
            <p>Let the brother of lowe degree reioyce in that he is exalted.</p>
            <p>Againe he that is rich in that he is made low: for as the flower of the graſſe ſhall he vaniſh away. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The firſt Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E heard in my reading the laſt Sabbath, by occaſion of the forerunning verſe, how odious before God, &amp; hatefull in his ſight, the ſinne of hypocriſie, and dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of mind is: eſpecially in religion, &amp; in the ſeruice of God: when men will beare fayre wether with the world, and ſeeme to carry good mindes, and vpright affections towards Sion, the true Church of God, and yet ſecretly worke the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous effect of thornes and prickes to the ſides thereof. As alſo when men wil make their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and religion, as it were a ſhipmans hoſe, and an indiferent thing, ſwearing by the Lord, and by <hi>Malcham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zephan. 1.5. 1 Kings. 18.21.</note> and halting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two opinions, as the people whome ſometimes <hi>Eliah</hi> the Prophet ſharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued becauſe they cared not whether
<pb facs="tcp:20078:9"/>
they worſhipped God, or Baall, and paſt not whether they ſerued God altogether, or in parte, with whom many of this our age doe iumpe, &amp; ioyne hands, who make conſcience of no religion: for whether it be the light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel, or the blindnes of poperie and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition that preuayleth, they eſteeme not, ſo that it ſerue for their commoditie, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, hauing a heart, and a heart, as the Greeke worde ſignificantly importeth,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> one for the olde lawe, and another for the newe learning, as they tearme it. But we ſhewed, and prooued both by teſtimonies, &amp; exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that as the ſinne of ſuch men is great, ſo is their ende horrible, and their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment greeuous many times in this life. And in the concluſion of my former lecture, it was further declared, that as it hapeneth in the ordinarie vſe, or rather abuſe of othes, that the man which is a common ſwearer will not ſticke ſometimes for his profite to forſweare himſelfe, the ſame ſinne being increaſed by practiſe, and by cuſtome grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to an habite in him: and as it comes to paſſe alſo amongſt murderers, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no conſcience of the ſlaughter of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent children, or ſeruants, will make no bones to proceede further, namely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue
<pb facs="tcp:20078:9"/>
their hands in the guiltleſſe blood of greater perſonages,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.33. &amp;c.</note> as appeareth by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the vineyard let out to the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who hauing ſlayne the houſhoulders ſeruants, did not ſpare to commit the like outrage, againſt his ſonne, and heyre, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the progreſſe of malice in the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who hauing murdred the prophets, crucified at laſt the <hi>Meſſias</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.1. Mat. 23.32</note> the heyre of all things, &amp; ſo fulfilled the meaſure of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: euen ſo it falleth out in the ſinne of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, that he that commonly exerciſeth double dealing, and diſſimulation in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters, will ſmell alſo of the ſame in the ſeruice of God, putting no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the holineſſe of religion, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe of his ordinarie dealings: ſo that whether he vſeth prayer, or frequenteth ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to heare, or whether he faſteth, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth almes, or whatſoeuer elſe is done by him in this caſe, it is done in that ſort as the counterfaite ſhewe of great deuotion was made by the people of <hi>Iuda,</hi> who although they vſed to ſay the Lord liueth,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.2.</note> yet they did ſweare falſely, &amp; as in that one, ſo in al other religious matters, they plaide the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits. And of ſuch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excellent Pſalme, contayning the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:10"/>
ſumme of al the benefites of the Lord, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and extended to his people the poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they remembred (ſaith he) that God was their ſtrength,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78 35.36.37.</note> and the moſt high God their redeemer, but they flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with their mouth, and diſſembled with him with their tongue, for their heart was not vpright with him, neither were they faithfull in his couenant. Meaning that their double dealing in his ſeruice was ſuch, and ſo great, as that they ranne vnto him, and ſought him early, as though they had beene very holy, and religious, but all was for feare of puniſhment, and not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearty loue, or obedience, that they did carry towards God. Whereby together with other reaſons, I confirmed the former ſententious ſpeech of <hi>Iames</hi> in the 8. verſe, that a double minded man is vnſtable not in one but in all his wayes: and ſo infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an exhortation, and direction, to pray vnto God to auoid, and flye from all the pointes and partes of hyprocriſie, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of heart, I ended for that time. Yt now followeth in the 9. verſe. <hi>Let the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lowe degree reioyce. &amp;c.</hi> In which words, the Apoſtle in my opinion ſeemeth to returne to the argument of ioy and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:20078:10"/>
to be vſed of vs in our aflictions wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as you haue already heard, he intreated before in the 2.3. &amp; 4. verſes of this preſent chapter. Which argument he hath hitherto left, &amp; broken of, with purpoſe to take away ſuch obiections as might be made and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med preiudiciall to the ſame doctrine and matter. For if you would for a triall as it were ſtrike, and race out the verſes interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwixt this 9. and the 4. then it would euidently appeare, and ye ſhould eaſily finde that this preſent verſe is in good order and artificiall method, added &amp; applied to the 4. verſe: for there the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; of perfection in patience conſiſting in perſeuerance in the time of trouble and aduerſitie, and now in this verſe he comes backe againe to the ſame argument, and proceedeth therein for the further comfort &amp; conſolation of the afflicted. And knowing that amongſt all the croſſes and calamities of this life, the croſſe of pouertie and of wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in reſpect of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon neceſſaries, is both very generall and very grieuous alſo, yea to the weake ſhoulders of fleſh &amp; blood almoſt intollerable, inſomuch that many times, yea dayly we ſee thoſe of that ſtate, which are not preuented with the grace of God nor go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned
<pb facs="tcp:20078:11"/>
by the ſpirit, and ſo not perſwaded to relie vppon the prouidence of God, and to content themſelues with their poore condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do breake the walles of obedience, and runne headlong into vnlawful actions and thereby into the daunger of the lawes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſatiſfie themſelues by thefte, and to relieue themſelues by robbery, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times murther the conſequence thereof, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſtand to the miſeries, and indigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of their vnfortunate place, the holy Apoſtle hauing a ſpecial conſideration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, doth heare by his counſell, and perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on labour to cure this malady, and to apply a ſalue to the ſore of the poore man, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his mind freely and ſufficiently in the matter. And if we do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diligence conſider, and with iudgment examine the contents of theſe verſes, we ſhal finde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle doth heare make, &amp; inſtitute a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon betwixt thoſe two diuers things, which oftentimes are occaſions of temptations &amp; prouocations to ſome diſorders &amp; miſchiefes in thoſe men which are within the compaſſe of the ſame, namely pouertie, &amp; riches, of the firſt wherof he ſpeakes in this 9. verſe, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other in the ſequell of the place, ſo that I take the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and order of theſe verſes conſiſting of
<pb facs="tcp:20078:11"/>
three ſeueral points to be this. Firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth enter into a courſe of ſchooling the poore man ſhewing him by direction, with what minde he is to take, and to beare the croſſe of his pouertie and howe to behaue himſelfe in the ſtate and time of his low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: that is, he is not to fire his eyes, and to looke onely vpon the vileneſſe, and baſeneſſe of his condition, and to dwell ſtill vpon the conſideration of his pinching neceſſities, but he is to take another, and better courſe, namely to erecte and lifte vp his minde in ſome heauenly meditation, to take as it were a ſpirituall view of that immortall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and celeſtiall poſſeſſion, wherein he ſhal be ioyned partener with al the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and children of God, if he practiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation, patience, obedience, &amp; godlines in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple life, whereby it pleaſeth God for a time to try &amp; to humble him. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond place he vndertaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admoniſhing &amp; aduiſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich man alſo, teaching him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what mind he is to take, &amp; in what ſort to vſe the bleſſing, &amp; abundance of his riches, to wit, he is not by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof to exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his conceit, &amp; to lift himſelf vp in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his happines, as though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his welth ſhould for euer continue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, &amp; he with it,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:12"/>
but he is to know that as his life is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſo is his riches, foraſmuch as the Lord giueth both, and taketh both away at his pleaſure: ſo that he is not to ware proud or to growe arrogant, vpon the taſt and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the felicitie of this life, but rather to be meekly ſpirited, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of his greateſt floriſhing, as knowing that although he be now at this preſent in much proſperitie, &amp; hoyſed vp to the top and mount of good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, yet he may ſuddenly be turned downe to miſerie, and ſtript of all that now he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth. Thirdly, and laſtly, leaſt the Apoſtle ſhould ſeeme to ſpeak this without his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and euidence, he doth in the latter parte of the tenthe verſe, produce a reaſon as an amplification of the doctrine, to fortifie his aſſertion withall, which is done by way of ſimilitude conſiſting of the qualitie and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur of a common flower of the graſſe, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the weake ſtate, and ſhort durance of humane proſperitie: then which flower ye know your ſelues there is nothing more mutable, and ſubiect to a change, by reaſon of the ſmall force, and ſubſtance that it hath to abide, and ſtand, in his beautie: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſpread it ſelfe gloriouſly in the morning, and ſeeme to be the thing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:20078:12"/>
nature hath labored to ſhew all her ſkill, yet the heate of the ſunne when it riſeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermatcheth the glorie thereof, and makes it quickly to wither, and come to nothing. Such is the rich man, and his riches. So that by this onely diuiſion, and reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the verſes ye may well conceiue what no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and neceſſary matter is lodged and contayned in them. Being ſuch, as doth concerne all eſtates, and reſpect all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, high and lowe, rich and poore, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonage and the pooreſt cotager, all and euery one may herehence learne a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for his life, and furniſh his minde with a ſufficient treaſure of inſtructions, how &amp; after what maner to diſpoſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his doings in the beſt ſort to the glorie of God, and the euerlaſting comfort of his ſoule. The poore man becauſe of his wants and defectes is not to deſpaire: the rich man by reaſon of his aboundance, and fuperfluities is not to preſume of himſelfe, and his abilitie: the honorable is to temper his high degree with humbleneſſe of minde, the Iazar or miſerable creature, to mitigate, and qualifie his ſmart by the vſe of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as hereafter in the proceſſe of our ſpeech yee ſhall ſee, by the grace of God,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:13"/>
more at large.</p>
               <p>Concerning therfore the firſt of our parts, although the Apoſtles phraſe be here ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſeeming to ſpeake of ſome ſpecial or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſon, yet by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring other places with it of the ſame forme of wordes, and by conſidering the reach of the doctrine to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend generally to all, I doubt not but they are plurally to be taken, and conſerued. For the propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being indefinite, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the place ſo ioyntly, and ſenſibly depending vpon the precedence it cannot be but equiualent, and the ſame with an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall ſpeech. To acquaint you with my meaning in plaine termes, albeit the Apoſtle doth heare ſay let the poore man, or <hi>brother of lowe degree reioyce,</hi> it is all one, or as much as if he had ſaid, let al poore men, and all breethren of low degree reioyce, becauſe that, which he requireth at the hands of one of that ſort, he looketh for of all, and if ye do with diligence note, and with iudgment co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſcripture ſpeeches, ye ſhall in many places light vpon wordes of the ſame courſe &amp; nature, deliuered in ſuch ſinguler maner and yet importing, and including vniuerſall conſtructions. In that the common name of a poore man is not heare vſed, but the appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb facs="tcp:20078:13"/>
of a brother, it may teach vs, what is to bee thought of ſuch a one vpon whom it hath pleaſed God to impoſe, and lay the croſſe of pouertie, in which caſe to bee taught, and informed, I take it to be very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, and neceſſary for many of vs: for we in our common iudgments are very carnall, and in our opinions fooliſh, who vſe to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the worthines of a man by the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and vpon the ſight and view of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery doe by and by pronounce him a wicked perſon, a vicious liuer, a man accurſed, and puniſhed in ſuch ſort deſeruedly for his ſins, when as the purpoſe of God in the viſiting of many with his croſſes, is not ſo much to notifie, and confirme to the world the deſerte in them of ſuch afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but either to make proofe &amp; trial of their faith, or elſe to conuert their humiliations to other good purpoſes, ſeruing for his glory &amp; their bettering. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is not one man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the ſons of men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting al of corrupt &amp; mortall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo holy, and righteouſe as that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth not any puniſhment or correction, if the Lorde woulde ſtraightly marke iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; do nothing but that, which the rules of his iuſtice doe preſcribe, who then ſhould ſtand; as the prophet ſpeakes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> but foraſmuch
<pb facs="tcp:20078:14"/>
as it hath pleaſed God in the aboundance of his loue, to take away the curſe of the lawe due for ſinne by the death of his ſonne and not to impute ſinne to him that beleeueth, and ſeeing the very faithfull themſelues are ſubiect to croſſes and afflictions ſundrie wayes, and in greater meaſure ſubiect then the children of vnbeleefe, it cannot be that troubles and calamities ſhould alwayes be demonſtrations of the wrath of God, or teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonies of great ſinnes in thoſe, whoſe ſhoulders lye vnder ſuch burdens. But we are otherwiſe to thinke, that ſometimes God doth diſcipline his children by the vſe of his rodde for ſome ſecret ſinnes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections which themſelues doe not eſpie: ſometimes hee doth before hande preuent their ſins the fruit of that corruption, which lyeth hidde in them and would otherwiſe break forth, except by ſickneſſe, pouertie, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, hunger, or ſuch like meanes they be admoniſhed, and reſtrayned: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he hath reſpect to his owne glorie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with iudgment at his owne houſe, leaſt he ſhould ſeeme to approue thoſe ſins in his elect, which his iuſtice doth more ſharpely puniſh in the reprobates: ſomtimes he doth ſuffer Satan that roaring Lyon &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:20078:14"/>
his miniſters, to haue after a ſorte power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſtates, and bodies of his children for the experiment of their conſtancie, and the inſtruction of others: and ſometimes alſo he doth vſe the daungers, &amp; extremities of the ſaints, as occaſions to ſhew foorth his owne power, glorie, mercie, wiſedome, and righteouſneſſe in his church, by miraculous deliuerances, bringing them into manifeſt perils, and yet finding meanes to preſerue them beyond the hope and opinions of men. Theſe together with other intentions in the workes of God if they be well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will bridle the ouerlaſhing humor of carnall iudgment, and leaue no roote of cauſe in the minde of any man, to take ſuch perſons for ſinners, and diſpiſed of God, whoſe liues are heare ſubiect to ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall difficulties. In the holy ſtorie of <hi>Iob,</hi> we read, that when his three friendes, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the euil that was come vnto him, came from their places to ſee him, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his caſe with him, &amp; beheld the great and ſtraunge miſerie wherevnto hee was brought, and the lamentable plight wherein he ſtood, they were ſo caried away with the ſtreame of a falſe imagination, and conceit concerning him that whereas before they
<pb facs="tcp:20078:15"/>
tooke him for an vpright, and iuſt man, and hygh in the fauour &amp; loue of God, they now vpon the appearance iudged him to be an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and ſpared not raſhly to affirme, that he was in that ſort &amp; meaſure iuſtly plagued of God for his his ſins: for <hi>Eliphaz</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Tema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> wiſhed him to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber and cal to minde who euer periſhed being an innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpright were deſtroied.<note place="margin">Iob. 4.7.</note> I haue ſeen it, ſaid he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which plow iniquitie, and ſow wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, do reape the ſame, ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluding, that <hi>Iob</hi> could not be innocent or vpright or free from wickednes, becauſe the fruit &amp; effect of ſuch miſfortunes, &amp; calamities was fallen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And I doubt not but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the ſame <hi>Eliphaz</hi> is a patterne of al carnally minded, &amp; ignorantly conceited worldlings, who vſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly to draw arguments from the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the children of God, ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are not good, nor honeſt, nor ſuch as they would ſeeme to be, becauſe they liue not in ſuch a free, &amp; happy, &amp; glorious ſtate of life, as others doe. Wherin they diſcouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be as brutiſh,<note place="margin">Now called Malta.</note> &amp; barbarous, as thoſe barbarians of the Ile of <hi>Melita,</hi> whereinto <hi>Paul</hi> happened after his eſcape from ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, who vpon the leaping of a Viper vpon his hande,<note place="margin">Acts. 28.4.</note> from the fire, condemned
<pb facs="tcp:20078:15"/>
him by &amp; by for a murderer, &amp; for ſuch a one as vengeance would not ſuffer to liue. This is in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> raſh verdits of our Atheiſtes, Epicures, Libertines, &amp; prophane Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who reſpecting nothing but the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accident, and not conſidering by reaſon of their naturall blindnes the courſe of God in his workes commit ſinne in their ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſpeaking good of euill, and euill of good,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.20.</note> ill of the righteous, &amp; well of the couetous whom God abhorreth. They may learne to correct their erroneous iudgments both by the ſequell of that place of the Acts before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by the anſwere of <hi>Iob,</hi> who to purge himſelfe, &amp; to defend his innocencie againſt the ouerhaſtie opinions of his friends affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord knew his way &amp; tryed him &amp; that he ſhould come forth like the golde:<note place="margin">Iob. 23.10.</note> meaning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> although the world was ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the true cauſe of his miſerie, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therof was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord, who vſed the ſame as a mean to bring to paſſe his greater profite. Let vs make ſome vſe then of this matter for our ſelues, &amp; know aſſuredly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as on the one ſide it is no ſufficient reaſon to proue the vertue, and goodnes of a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath welth and riches in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo on the other ſide it is no neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:20078:16"/>
concluſion to condemne a man for wicked, and vnrighteouſe, becauſe he is afflicted with pouertie and lacke of ſufficient reliefe for himſelfe, the remembrance, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherof, wil work in vs a charitable, and Chriſtian opinion concerning our poore brethren, not to thinke that they are the worſe men in the ſight of God becauſe of their harde happe in that caſe, they are our brethren ſtill, in profeſſion, and eſſence, fleſh of our fleſh, bone of our bone, of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in making, and of the ſame mettle in ſubſtance, whereof we our ſelues bee wee neuer ſo daintie, are created, and therefore they are not to be vſed of vs with ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and indignitie as they receiue gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of the worlde: foraſmuch as it is not their pouertie that doth either alter their nature which is ſtill common with ours, or proue them to be diſfauored of the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> the caſe ſo ſtanding, that whom God loueth he chaſteneth, and hee ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth, and the affliction of a baſe eſtate, is many times to the man rather an argument of the loue of God then a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his wrath: as appeareth expreſly by the wordes of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greeuouſly afflicted himſelfe, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:20078:16"/>
the purpoſe of God therein ſufficiently, doth pronounce a bleſſing to thoſe that did pittie his caſe, and conceiue a good opinion of him, and of all thoſe, which ſhould be in the like ſort viſited: for he breaketh forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this effectuall ſpeech,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1.</note> bleſſed is he that iudgeth wiſely of the poore, the Lorde ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble. Meaning ſuch a one as doth not condemne that man for accurſed whom God doth afflict with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie knowing that there are many cauſes, why his hand is in ſuch ſort heauie vpon a man. Secondly by this appellation and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of brother which the Apoſtle doth heere apply to the poore man, we may learne by his example how to vſe our words, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our ſpeeches concerning men of baſe place, and ſtate. To giue them the beſt ſtile that we can, and to auoyd the intemperate humors of many diſdainfull perſons, who cannot frame their tongues to any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent words reſpecting their inferiors, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile them, and taunte them, and loade them with ſuch contemptuous tearmes, as are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comely in their owne mouthes, nor in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorte fitting the perſons towardes whom they vſe ſuch immoderation.<note place="margin">Prou. 17.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that he that hath knowledge ſpareth
<pb facs="tcp:20078:17"/>
his words.<note place="margin">Iames. 4.11.</note> And our Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> will haue vs in no caſe to ſpeake euil one of another. A third matter there is alſo in theſe wordes, which is not to be omitted without note and obſeruation, namely that in the Apoſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections heere to the poore man, and in the vſe of his name, he doth not cal him the poore brother, or beggerly brother, but the brother of low degree, although in ſo doing it may ſeeme that part of his meaning is to increaſe and magnifie the glorious exaltation of ſuch a man to the kingdome of God, which by a compariſon made with a precedent baſenes, is made ſo much the more high and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, by how much the more low and ſimple his condition was before in the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that contrary things being one ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, are then moſt cleerely and perfectly ſeen what they are, yet I doubt not but that the commodities of the low eſtate of a poore man, are heere inſinnuated, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by the vſe of the phraſe: for the low degree of a man, although it bee accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſome wants in reſpecte of the abundance of the richer ſorte, who are commonly deſtitute of nothing ſeruing to the outward proſperitie of this life, yet it is free from thoſe hazardes, and perilles,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:17"/>
whereunto the hygh eſtate of the welthy is continually ſubiecte. For they may in good ſenſe bee compared to hyghe trees ſcituated and planted in the toppes of mountayns, which by reaſon of their place lye open to euery winde that bloweth, and euery ſtorme that aryſeth, yea a little puffe of the ayre maketh them to ſhake, and to tremble: but the poorer ſorte are with good probabilitie reſembled to lowe ſhrubbes, or buſhes growing in the vallies vnder the winges, and defence of the hilles, which by reaſon of their lowe growth, are ſafe from the raging ſtorme, and beating tempeſt, they are not aſſaulted with the feerceneſſe of euery whirlewinde, they are not beaten with the droppes of euery ſcouring ſhowre, they ſtand and ſpring in quiet, and ſafetye, when the highe Cedars muſt needes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue euery wether, and refuſe none, and therefore are many times by contrary and furious windes rent and torne, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented of further increaſe. And many times we ſee great and mightie trees by violence of the wind ouerthrowen broken and pluckt vp by the rootes, ſeldome or neuer doth the like ouerthrowe happen to a lowe and litle buſh. Againe the hygher &amp; ſtatelier the tree
<pb facs="tcp:20078:18"/>
is the more terible is his fall, and the more ſigne, and impreſſion thereof doth he make in the earth: the buſh or bramble ſuppoſe he be rooted vp and throwen downe hee falles without any harme, and perceth not. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if a great tree fall, all the bowes and branches, that are on his falling parte are bruſed, and cruſht vnder him: but ſo is it not in the ſhrubbe: for as his leaues be few and his branches ſmall, ſo is his danger the leſſe, and his harme none at all. All which things the riche man for his admonition, and the poore man for his comforte, are to apply to themſelues. The riche man whether wee conſider him in reſpect of his conceit, or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie of his place, he is a high tree, in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit many times he is ſuch a one, as ſtands within the threat of the prophet <hi>Eſay.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 2.12.13.</note> The day of the Lord of hoſts is vpon al the proud and hautye and vpon all that is exalted, and ſhalbe made low, euen vpon all the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that are high, and exalted, and vpon all the Okes of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and vpon all the high mountaines, and vpon all the hils that are lifted vp: meaning in that place by the high trees, and hils, ſuch manner of men as are lifted vp in pride, and growen loftely minded by reaſon of their welth gathered by
<pb facs="tcp:20078:18"/>
coueteouſneſſe, thinking themſelues thereby to be towers, and walles, as it followeth in the fifteenth verſe of that chapter, that is ſtronge, and mightie of themſelues, not able to bee ouerthrowen. And doubtleſſe many ſuch high trees, I meane many high ſpirited men there are amongſt vs, who being raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and caried away with an opinion of themſelues, are altogether forgetful of their mortall ſtate, they thinke with the king of <hi>Babell,</hi> that they ſhall liue for euer, they ſaye with <hi>Nimrodde</hi> and his company,<note place="margin">Gen. 11 4.</note> let vs build and get vs a name, they truſt in their goods, &amp; boaſt themſelues in the multitude of their riches, they thinke their houſes and their habitations ſhal continue for euer, euen from generation to generation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.6.11.13.</note> and cal their lands by their names. But what ſayeth the prophet concerning the end of ſuch men, this their way vttereth their fooliſhnes, for their beautie ſhall conſume when they ſhall goe from their houſe to the graue. And in the propheſie of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 31.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> there is a notable place to this purpoſe, where the prophet ſpeaking of the king of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> affirmeth that once he was like a Cedar in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> with fayre branches, and thicke ſhadowing bowes, and ſhot vp very high, and his top was amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:20078:19"/>
the thicke bowes, his height was exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the trees of the fieeld.<note place="margin">verſe. 11.12.</note> &amp;c. but what followes in the place, thus ſaith the Lord I haue caſt him away for his wickedneſſe, his branches are fallen, his bowes are broken, all the people of the earth are departed from his ſhadowe, and haue forſaken him, yea hee is gone downe to hell. This is the ende of ſuch a highe tree, and the effect of ſuch lofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, verifying that famous ſentence of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in his Prouerbs,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.16.</note> that pride goeth before deſtruction, and an high minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fall. Which thing, is of ſome conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to be learned of all men for warning, and to bee conſidered of ſuch men for amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, as are ſubiecte to this ſinne: who if they cannot, and care not to reforme them ſelues by that which already hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken yet they are to remember further the iudgment of that highe tree, that proude king <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> who in the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Eſay</hi> is compared with <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 24.13.</note> which ſaide in his heart, I will climbe vp into heauen, and exalte my throne beſides the ſtarres of God &amp;c. But what followeth? thou ſhalt bee brought downe to the ground and to the ſides of the pitte, and more of his deſtruction yee ſhall finde, if yee reade
<pb facs="tcp:20078:19"/>
the chapter. Nowe in place and degree, the riche man alſo is a high tree, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof ſubiecte to many inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: euery ſharpe winde of alteration in the common wealth, of inuaſions of the enimie, and of other grieuous accidents driueth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: and not ſo onely, but in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes his heigth is alſo daungerous.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.5.8.6.</note> For an hard iudgment ſhall they haue that beare rule, ſo ſayeth the wiſe man: and againe, for the mightie abideth the ſorer triall: and againe, the mightie ſhalbe mightilie tormented, but hee that is moſt lowe is worthy of mercie.<note place="margin">Verſe. 6.</note> The poore man being a lowe ſhrubbe or buſhe is not ſo ſubiecte to the Are, to mutations, to iudgmentes, hee eſcapeth in ſafetie when the riche man is rifled, cruſhed, and by his mightie fall, like a greate ſtone from the toppe of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is daſhed into many peeces, and ſo his fall made vnrecouerable: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is better in my opinion to bee <hi>Abſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> his mule,<note place="margin">Abſtemij fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula.</note> though carrying great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of wood euery day with peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then bee his palfrey cladde in purple, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with furniture of Golde, and fedde with the beſt prouinder, and ſubiecte to the fearres and wounds, receiued commonly
<pb facs="tcp:20078:20"/>
in the warres. And this being conſidered I doe not ſee why the brother of lowe degree that is, the poore man, ſhould not according to the Apoſtles wordes, rather be glad then any way penſiue, foraſmuch as hee ſtands farre of from thundring, and gunſhotte: as his ſtate is lowe, ſo are his miſchiefes few, as his degree is not high, ſo his fall is not to be feared: but bee it that he doth fall, yet being within the compaſſe of the Lords protection, it is no otherwiſe then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.24.</note> though hee fall hee ſhall not be cut off, for the Lord putteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand, the Lord ſupporteth, and ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him vp ſo that in his fall there is no harme. The ſpeciall doctrine then that this conſideration, and matter yeeldeth, is not onely a comforte to the poore man, to holde himſelfe contented with his ſtate, becauſe of the benefite, and commoditie of ſafetye which it beareth in diuers reſpectes, but a perſwaſion &amp; counſell alſo to the rich man, not to be caried away with the ytching vayn of ambition, not to hunt with greedineſſe after promotion, not to bee poſſeſſed with ſuch vayneglorious humors, as were the Scribes,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.6.7.</note> and the Phariſies, who loued the cheife places at feaſtes and the higheſt ſeats
<pb facs="tcp:20078:20"/>
in the aſſemblies, and greetinges in the market, and to be called of men <hi>Rabbi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi.</hi> It is an inreuocable decree, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will exalte himſelfe ſhalbe brought low, and humbled. Somewhat it was that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi> the yongeſt ſonne of <hi>Ierubbaal,</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the toppe of mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudges. 9.8.</note> after that <hi>Abimelech</hi> the Tyrant had vſurped the kingdome and ſlaine his brethren the ſonnes of <hi>Ierubbaal</hi> about 70. perſons vpon one ſtone in propounding his parable to the men of <hi>Shechem</hi> affirmed, that when the trees went out to conſult about the electing, and annoynting of a king ouer them, it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the oliue that would leaue his fatneſſe, nor the figge tree his ſweetneſſe, nor the vine his wine, none of theſe trees, being indeed worthy of preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t would aduance themſelues to the gouernement and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but the contemptible bramble and ſcratching bryer whereunto <hi>Iotham</hi> likened the ſame <hi>Abimelech,</hi> he in the pride of his heart and the arrogancie of his ſtomacke, would needes take vpon him the ſtate and be Lorde ouer the reſt, not contenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with that place, which nature and birth had aſſigned him: but his highe conceite went before his fal and his ambitious ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:20078:21"/>
was rewarded with a miſerable deſtruction. And therefore in this caſe the anſwere of <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Michal</hi> his wife, who deſpiſed him becauſe of his dauncing, and reioycing and prayſing of God before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke, is generally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended I wil be yet more vile ſaid he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.22</note> &amp; wilbe low in mine own ſight, and of the very ſame maide ſeruants which thou haſt ſpoken of ſhall I be had in honour. So that the firſt ſteppe to true honour in deed is the practiſe of lowlineſſe, and a minde free from the infection of an ambitious appetite, by the vſe whereof, although a man may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſometimes by the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God aſpire to dignities, and offices of high place, yet the ſame is nothing elſe, but a meane and preparatiue to a greater miſchiefe, and ouerthrowe. So that my meaning in this matter may bee eaſily conceiued, which is, not to condemne a lawfull authoritie, nor to diſſwade any man from the vndertaking of ſuch roomes of credit and eſtimation as are of greate neceſſitie in the common wealth, and profitable for the peace and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſame, but my purpoſe onely is by occaſion of my terte to reproue the extremitie, which conſiſteth in a thyrſt
<pb facs="tcp:20078:21"/>
and hunger to be aloft and to exceeded the common ſtate of men: when a man follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vnbridled ſway of his proud conceit doth diſdayne the ſocietie, and company of his honeſt brethren, as not brooking any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie: ſaying with <hi>Adonijah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Haggith</hi> I will be king,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 1.5.</note> and with <hi>Aaman</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hammedatha</hi> the <hi>Agagite,</hi> all the honour, and glory that I haue, doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile me,<note place="margin">Heſter 5.13.</note> as long as I ſee <hi>Mordecaye</hi> the <hi>Iew</hi> ſitting at the kings gate. This is it that I ſpeake of, and againſt a climing humor, a brambles ſpirite, a diſpoſition inclining to preheminence, not with intent to doe any common good to the countrey, but with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe onely to feede, and ſatiſfie the roote of arrogancie, and ambition, to commaund all men, and to be ſubiect to no man. Which I take to be reprooued by him, whoſe life was the ſpectacle and preſident of all humilitie, ye receiue honour one of another,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.44.</note> and ſeeke not the honour that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of God. Which is a thing generally founde in theſe dayes, and therefore requires a generall warning. For euen amongſt vs there are thoſe, who although they are not furniſhed with any excellent gifte or grace of God, and haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge in them deſeruing commendation,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:22"/>
ſaue onely a little more money, and welth then their neighbours haue, yet they are ſo vnreaſonably ledde away with the force of this inſolent conceit, as that they vouchſafe not a good looke towards thoſe, who albeit they poſſeſſe not ſo much wealth, yet they practiſe more vertue, and honeſtie, then the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And there are many petty <hi>Abſolom</hi> alſo floriſhing amongſt vs, nothing but the crowne and kingdome, I meane the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracye, and roome of Iuſtice can content them, inſomuch that there is no reſt of their continuall laborings, till they come to ſitte downe in the chayre of <hi>Dauid,</hi> in that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend place which requireth a great meaſure of iudgment, wiſedome, experience, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and conſcience, from all which things they are as farre, as they are neere vnto the gall and bitterneſſe of preſumption. So that I ſee the date of that auncient propheſie of the holy Apoſtle out, and expired, who long agoe foreſawe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 3.1.</note> that in the laſt dayes there ſhould come perilous times, men ſhould bee louers of their owne ſelues, couetous, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, proud &amp;c. intemperate, ferce, no louers at all of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are good, heady, high minded louers of pleaſure more then louers of God: the full accompliſhment of which propheſie
<pb facs="tcp:20078:22"/>
whoſoeuer ſeeth not, ſeeth nothing. But as the Apoſtle propheſied of ſuch men, ſo may we propheſie of the ende of them, not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the ſpirites of prophetes, but collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the ends of other men, who in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance were in ſuch ſorte affected, and therefore euen in this life taſted the bitter fruite of their owne workes and qualities, that the reward whereof the Apoſtle heere ſpeaketh, and promiſeth remayning for the brother of low degree, which is exaltation, and great glorye, ſhalbe no parte of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, becauſe they ſmell not of the ſwete ſpirite of humilitie, which is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and ſteppe to that high degree of true honour, and felicitie, which is proper onely to ſuch, and reſerued onely for ſuch, as doe decke themſelues inwardly with lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind and humble them ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.5.6.</note> to whom there is a promiſe of exalting made in due &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time. The Apoſtle hauing thus v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the name of the poore man, doth nowe proceed to his purpoſe, namely to direct him to that thing, which in the time of his pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he is to practiſe, &amp; that is ioy, for ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the verſe. <hi>Let the brother of lowe degree reioyce.</hi> He might haue ſaid let him
<pb facs="tcp:20078:23"/>
not bee ſorie, or let him not bee impatient, or let him contente himſelfe, or any ſuch like thing, which might well haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed both with his intent and with the poore mans qualitie, but hee vſeth here a word of greater effect and force, <hi>Let him reioyce,</hi> whereby he doth labour to remoue all ſorrow and ſadnes from the minde of the poore man, wiſhing him not to bee heauy in heart, nor dolefull in conceit, but rather to plucke vp his ſpirite, to bee of good cheer, and comfort, yea to conceiue gladneſſe in the time of his greateſt ſmarte of pouertie, vpon conſideration of the high degree of glorie &amp; felicitie whereunto it is the purpoſe of God to exalte him, wherehence euery one, that is ſubiect to the croſſe of pouertie may drawe out for himſelfe a ſinguler conſolation, and learne withall how he is beſt to behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when his ſhoulders are cruſht with the ſame burden, and yoke, how to ſupport, and ſtrengthen himſelfe, leaſt he fall into theſe daungerous miſchiefes and inconueniences, which the maior part of that ſorte, being deſtitute of grace &amp; gouernement, doe daily runne into: his beſt courſe is, to fixe his eyes, by the vſe of his hope &amp; faith vpon the crown of righteouſnes, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord the righteous
<pb facs="tcp:20078:23"/>
Iudge hath laid vp, and wil giue to al thoſe that loue his appearing, and in a ioyfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the ſame, doe with quietneſſe ſuſtayne, and with patience goe thorow this ſpeciall affliction, knowing that it pleaſeth God ſometimes to vſe the ſame as a meane or inſtrument to bring a man to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, to faith, repentance, prayer, obedience, and other Chriſtian dueties, and at the laſt to the end of his faith, which is the ſaluation of his ſoule. So that although I muſt needes confeſſe that on the one ſide the drinking of this bitter cup, and the feeling of the miſeries of this ſtate may diſcourage a man, and driue him to the doore of faintnes, and almoſt diſpayre, yet on the other ſide the remembrance of the promiſed glorie of God to come, and aſſuredly to be ſhewed may as a ſweete and pleaſant draught extinguiſh the former bitterneſſe, and turne the ſtrong ſtreame of impatiencie into a quietneſſe of contentation, to effectuate therby that ſame practiſe of ioy whereunto he is heere, as it were by the hande of the Apoſtle ledde and conducted in the mides of his calamitie. And for the better helpe and furtherance of the poore man to this good vſe and practiſe, and to cauſe him both the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:24"/>
and the more plentifully alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this ioy he is with ſome diligence to ponder with himſelfe the moſt louing courſe that it hath pleaſed God to take with him ouer and aboue the maner of dealing hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with and towards the rich man. For whereas he is moſt vſually in the leaues of the ſcriptures reproued, threatned, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and wiſhed to mourne and lament, the poore man contrarywiſe is comforted, incouraged, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, and willed to reioice, as in this place. In the fift chapter of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles,<note place="margin">Verſe. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iames</hi> ſinges another maner of ſonge to the richer ſort: goe too now ye rich men weep and houle for the miſeries which ſhall come vpon you, your riches are corrupt, and your garmentes are motheaten, your gold and ſiluer is cancred, and the ruſt of them ſhalbe a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eate your fleſh as it were fire. &amp;c. which wordes I could wiſh were written in ſome place ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the eyes of al of that ſorte, that ſeeing of themſelues they will not remember, yet by this meanes they might alwayes bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of their great abuſes committed in the bleſſings of God, and of the plagues which thoſe abuſes will bring vpon them without ſpeedy, and harty repentance. But
<pb facs="tcp:20078:24"/>
for our vſe, I note thus much by comparing theſe two places together: that the common ſort of rich men are wonderfully deceiued in their opinion, and doe mightily erre in their conceite, who imagine that the onely true ioy and pleaſure conſiſteth in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of riches, and in the inioy of wealth, to be able to tell much money, to produce good ſtore of golde, to be able to buy, and builde, and by continuall purchaſe to ioyne land to lande, houſe to houſe, and Lordſhippe to Lordſhippe, ſo to liue, and dwell as princes of the earth, this is the mother of ioye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: by occaſion whereof they ſing and reioyce and ſlay oxen, and kill ſheepe,<note place="margin">Eſai. 22.13.</note> &amp; eate fleſh, and drinke wine, and ſay, let vs eate and drinke for to morow we ſhall die: but this ioy proceeding not from God nor his ſpirite, who is the Author and fountaine of all Chriſtian and lawfull reioycing, is no true ioy, but rather a madnes and frantike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when as men forgetting themſelues, and not conſidering the vanitie of their mindes, the breuitie of their pleaſures, and the vncertainty of proſperity, and carnall wealth, doe reioyce in their boaſtings,<note place="margin">Iames 4.16, Act. 7.41.</note> and in the woorkes of their owne handes, yea in a thing of nought and ſay, haue not we got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:20078:25"/>
vs hornes by our owne ſtrength?<note place="margin">Amos 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> I deny not but that riches being well vſed, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to their right endes, namely to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Gods glory, the preferment of his worde, the profite of his Church, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of the poore, and ſuch other good &amp; holie purpoſes a man in the performance of theſe dueties, may reioyce with thankes to God, that it pleaſed him to work in his heart ſuch acceptable motions, and to diſpoſe him to the exerciſe of the fruites of his faith for the diſcharge of his conſcience, and the prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of others to the like obedience, but to thinke that where wealth and proſperitie is abuſed, beeing conuerted to the nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of pride, prodigalitie, banquetting, couetouſneſſe, oppreſſion, vſurie, reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſuch like wicked actions, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which men take, and the ioy which they conceiue to be good or honeſt, or any way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, is an opinion very abſurd, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the braine of a Chriſtian. And yet there are ſuch amongſt vs, who being hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winked with the vayle of carnall conceite, doe as it were clappe their handes, and throwe vp their cappes at their good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, triumphing in the increaſe of their wealth and making bankets becauſe of their
<pb facs="tcp:20078:25"/>
abundance, and goe no further, eyther to the acknowledging of the goodnes of God, from whence all good thinges proceede, or to the directing of their riches to ſuche vſes as by duetie, and conſcience they are bounde vnto. In ſuche caſes they ought rather to weep and howle as <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, becauſe all good ſenſe and feeling is taken away from them, and their heartes not moued by the bleſſinges of God towardes them, to bee thankefull to him for the ſame, and to fructifie in good workes to the praiſe of his name, and the good of his Church. Againe on the other ſide alſo, the poore man is not free from errour, nor to bee excuſed in his opinion, who by reaſon of the wantes of his ſtate, and the manifolde miſeries which by compulſion hee is driuen to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, doeth quite baniſhe from his heart all ioy, and gladnes, applying no comfort to his mynde, no peace to his ſpirites, no ſolace to his ſoule, but paſſing his time in miſerable carefulneſſe, and languiſhing by the force of his imagination. Hee is in this caſe for his correction, and remedie, to haue recourſe to the word of God, and to deriue out for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thoſe ſweet promiſes, which are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made and leueled therein towards him, to
<pb facs="tcp:20078:26"/>
keepe him from all ſuch miſchiefes, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe and ſtay thereof, he might dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly fall into. <hi>Salomon</hi> that prince of peace, and of wiſedome alſo, in his booke of Prouerbes, or notable ſentences, affirmeth that a little with the feare of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Prou. 15.16</note> is better then great treaſure, &amp; trouble there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as commonly it happeneth to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſort, who take not ſo much payne to get as they are diſquieted with carke, and care, to preſerue and increaſe that which they haue gotten, and therefore the ſpirite of God by the Apoſtle condemneth them,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.10.</note> as men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pierced themſelues thorow with many ſorowes, reaping an euill conſcience, as the fruite or harueſt of their couetous labours.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo in that excellent Pſalme which containeth matter of incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and conſolation, to ſuch as marke and grieue at the proſperitie of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and doe after a ſort ſtagger in faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the contrary, which is affliction, &amp; croſſes, wherewith the children of God are alwayes compaſſed, hee doeth amongeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things miniſter a comfort to the heart, and conſcience of the weake, like and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 16.</note> pronouncing that a ſmall thing vnto the iuſt man is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:20078:26"/>
then great riches to the wicked, &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The reaſon is, becauſe the iuſt man, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be poore in condition, yet hee is riche in ſpirite and minde, becauſe he depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vppon the promiſe and prouidence of God, and contenteth himſelfe with his ſmall portion. But the vnrighteous man, though poſſeſſing much externall wealth is nothing ſo bleſſed nor happie as the poore man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is neuer ſatiſfied: he is like vnto the horſeleech, who hath two daughters crying,<note place="margin">Prou. 30.15.</note> giue, giue, he is like vnto the barren wombe, and the graue which will neuer bee full, and like to a man that hath the dropſie, who the more he drinketh, thinking thereby to extinguiſh his thyrſt, the more hee doeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the drieneſſe thereof, ſo the couetous riche man, the more hee hath, the more hee wanteth, and the more hee aboundeth, the more he thinketh himſelfe deſtitute, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore careth not what vnlawfull meanes hee vſeth to make his commoditie, hauing no feeling of conſcience, and no ſparkle of the feare of God in him. And therfore it is that the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reſolutely affirmeth in this matter, that godlines is great gaine,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.6.</note> if a man carrie a contentation, and a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of minde. For therein conſiſteth the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:27"/>
true ſufficiencie of this life, and without it, there is nothing els but the verie plague of greedines,<note place="margin">Ibid. 10.</note> and of vnſatiable auarice, which is the roote of all euill. And to theſe places we may adde alſo that ſame proteſtation of the Prophet, made for the increaſe of his owne comfort, and of others in ſuch ſorte minded as him ſelfe, beyng grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tryall and experience which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had gotten in the courſe and race of his whole life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.25.</note> profeſſing that hee had beene young, and was then olde, yet he neuer ſaw the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeede beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging bread. Which is a ſpeeche full of ſweet incouragement to the faithfull man, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, that howſoeuer it pleaſeth God for his triall to afflict him with pouertie, &amp; externall wantes, ſo that hee hath not the like fulneſſe and meaſure of releefe as the vngodlie man hath, yet he is neuer forſaken of the loue and fauour of God towards him, but is in ſuch ſorte regarded, and bleſſed of him, that although hee leade a poore life, and is not furniſhed with plentie of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thinges, yet that carnall want is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, &amp; recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, with ſtore of ſpiritual graces, which are the onely true treaſure, &amp; riches which cannot periſh, wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:20078:27"/>
no doubt ſpeaketh to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when he ſaith concerning himſelfe, &amp; other his fellow workers, that they were as ſorrowing, and yet alwayes reioycing, as hauing nothing,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.10.</note> &amp; yet poſſeſſing all thinges. And our Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> alſo vrgeth the ſame to the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the rich, after this ſorte. Hearken my beloued brethren,<note place="margin">Iames. 2.5.</note> hath not God choſen the poore of this world, that they ſhoulde bee rich in faith and heyres of the kingdome which hee hath promiſed to them that loue him? Thereby conuincing the rich men of the worlde, of parcialitie, and euil iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in their thoughtes by their owne confeſſion, becauſe they knew that God had promiſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inheritance of his kingdome to the poore, &amp; had adorned them with the riches and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of faith,<note place="margin">Math. 5.3.</note> and yet they vſed reſpect of perſons, yea, they deſpiſed the poore, and oppreſſed them by tyrannie, &amp; drew them before iudgement ſeates. The like argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth in another place of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> where ſpeaking of the ſtate of the Church of God in <hi>Corinth,</hi> which conſiſted but of meane, and ſimple perſons, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding confounded, and ouerthrew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſedome of the Scribe, &amp; the eloquence of the diſputer, and the vnderſtanding of all the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:28"/>
Philoſophers of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.26.27.</note> he remembreth the ſame Church thereof in theſe wordes. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren you ſee your calling, how that not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wiſe men after the fleſh, not many migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not many noble are called, but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the worlde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe, and the weake thinges of the world to confounde the mighty things, and vile things of the worlde, and things that are deſpiſed, hath God choſen, yea thinges which are in mans iudgement nothing, to bring to nought things that are. So that the poore man vpon the conſideration of this, that although hee ſwimmeth not in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde commodities of this life, as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doe, yet poſſeſſeth in good meaſure the graces, and bleſſings of the ſpirite, whereby that which is otherwiſe wanting, and defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in his ſtate is furniſhed in his minde, hereupon with good reaſon, and iuſtly hee may ſeparate all ſorowe, and lamentation from his heart, and diſpoſe him ſelfe to ſome comfort, and chriſtian reioycing, and teſtifie with the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſalme 4.7.</note> Thou O Lord haſt giuen me more ioy of heart then the ſonnes of men haue had when their wheate, and their wine did abound: Let worldlings therefore tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the ruffe of their pleaſures,<note place="margin">verſe 6.</note> and ſay
<pb facs="tcp:20078:28"/>
who will ſhew vs any good? that is plant their ioye and felicitie in riches, and in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting the vaine delights of this life, let the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolace himſelf with the light of the Lords countenance, &amp; with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his fauor, which he may aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be greater riches, than all the Golde of <hi>Ophyr</hi> which is in <hi>India,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Kin. 9.28. 2. Chron. 9.14.</note> or the Siluer which <hi>Salomon</hi> had from the Kings of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:20078:29"/>
               <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are not to pretermit in this matter an examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the latter parte of that notable proteſtation of the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the laſt day out of the thirtie and ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pſalme, where for the conſolation of the poore, iuſt, and righteouſe man hee profeſſeth that as hee had neuer ſeene himſelfe forſaken of the Lorde, ſo alſo hee had neuer ſeene his ſeede left ſo barely, or driuen to ſuch extremities, as that they were forced to begge their breade: a thing, which the poore man is with ſome diligence to conſider as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for the better ingendring of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation and comfort: for whereas the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the poore mans miſerie conſiſteth many times in the view of his wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whoſe minde by reaſon of them is ſo much the more oppreſſed with care, by how much the leſſe he ſeeth any ordinary meanes to leaue them after his death in any good or reaſonable ſtate, it cannot bee, but that when hee ſhall finde out a remedie for this ſpeciall griefe hee ſhall with great alacritie
<pb facs="tcp:20078:29"/>
applie himſelf to the conceiuing of this ioy, whereof he is here by the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. This ſalue or remedy, the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> will quickely giue him, for he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of the poore man, where the wound or ſore lyeth, proteſting in the worde of a prophet, and man of God, that the ſeede of the righteouſe man was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene by him begging bread. Which wordes are not ſo to bee taken, as though the iſſue of the righteouſe man, ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lefte in ſuch ſufficient caſe in reſpect of outward things as that they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer want any thing ſeruing for ſupplying of corporall wants, but the ſenſe of the words is, that the aflictions of this life, and the vſe of the Lords trials is not alwayes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent, nor continually remayning in the ſeede and poſteritie, of a righteouſe man, but that all the corrections of the Lorde vſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them are momentany and for a time, and indure not alwayes: ſo that although himſelfe doth dye, and be vntimely taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his children, yet the Lorde who prouided for him in the time of his life wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be carefull for his poſteritie after his death, ſo that they ſhall inioy his good bleſſings, and bee preſerued for euermore.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.28.</note> Whereas
<pb facs="tcp:20078:30"/>
on the contrary the ſeede of the wicked man ſhalbe cut off.<note place="margin">verſu eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pſal. 109.10.</note> His children ſhalbe vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and begge their bread, comming out of their deſtroyed places: his poſteritie ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be conſumed, and in the generation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his name ſhalbe put out: yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iniquitie of ſuch childrens fathers ſhalbe had in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall remembrance with the Lord, ſo that according to the tenor, &amp; courſe of the threat contayned in the lawe, the ielouſie, and fire of the Lordes wrath ſhalbe kindled ſo hot, and ſhall burne ſo furiouſly, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually againſt them that their iniquitites ſhabe viſited vpon the children,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> vpon the third, and fourth generation, of them that hate him: but on the contrary the beames of his mercie, and the ſunne ſhine of his fauour ſhal ſtretch, &amp; be extended vnto thouſands to them that loue him, and keepe his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. The performance of which graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſe, if there be any that ſtand doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of, and therefore ſeeme to diſtruſt the former profeſſion of the prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee that the ofſpring of many good and righteous men doe not inioy the ſame promiſed bleſſing, but are oftentimes left very ſimplye, and driuen to many inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, inſomuch that without the helpe
<pb facs="tcp:20078:30"/>
and releefe of others, they might not onely begge but famiſh and periſhe, and come to a lamentable ende, they that pauſe vpon this matter, and ſuſpend their iudgement, as not crediting the truth of the promiſe, nor the report of <hi>Dauid,</hi> are firſt to conſider, that it is a part of the performance of the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that it pleaſeth God by his ſpeciall prouidence to moue the hearts of good men to ſhew compaſſion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſolate and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe children of a righteouſe man, to be taken vp of them, and preſerued by them from the common miſeries and miſhappes of the worlde, whereas on the contrary the ſame prophet hath conſtantly affirmed, that for a full puniſhment of the ſinnes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.12.</note> it ſhall ſo come to paſſe after them that there ſhalbe none to extend mercie vnto them, neither any to ſhewe pittie vpon his fatherleſſe children. Againe they are in this matter to carry a good eye, and ſound iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to compare ſcripture with ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to conſider what the Lord ſpeaketh to this purpoſe by his prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> wher hee makes this promiſe conditionall. If a ſonne ſhall ſee the ſins of his father, &amp; feare,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.14.11.16.</note> and not doe the like, &amp;c. he ſhal not dye in the iniquitie of his father, but hee ſhall ſurely
<pb facs="tcp:20078:31"/>
liue: but if the ſon be cruel, a ſhedder of blood, an adulterer, an oppreſſor, an vſurer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intereſt, if he doth theſe things, ſaith the Lord, ſhal he liue? he ſhal not liue: ſeeing he hath done all theſe abominations he ſhal d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the death, and his blood ſhalbe vpon him: for ye ſee how this matter ſtandeth.<note place="margin">Verſe 10.11.12.13.</note> You muſt needs confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeing God doth not afflict nor puniſh any man iniuriouſly or vniuſtly therfore the affliction, and miſerie which the poſteritie of a righteouſe man are ſomtimes ſubiect vnto, proceede not from any rigor, or too much ſeueritie in God, but from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart of their owne actuall, and perſonall ſinnes, God is not ſo cruell or prepoſterous in his iuſtice as to puniſh one man for the ſinne of another: ye ſhall vſe this prouerbe no more ſayth the Lord, the fathers haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſowre grapes,<note place="margin">verſe 1.4.</note> &amp; the childrens teeth are ſet on edge, but the ſoule that ſinneth that ſoule ſhall dye: and therefore the ſenſe of the law in <hi>Exodus</hi> is this: God will viſite the iniquitie of fathers vpon their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: true, if they hate him, if they proceede, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the ſins of their fathers: otherwiſe if they forſake their fathers ſins, they ſhal not feele their fathers plagues. And againe. God wil ſhew mercie vnto thouſands: true, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20078:31"/>
that loue him, that keep his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, that do continue and goe forward in their fathers obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; holines: but if they break of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe, &amp; practiſe of their fathers vertue, they ſhal cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the taſt of their fathers bleſſings: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> although amongſt vs many times it comes to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the children of a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of a zealous proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vnſpotted in his life, are deſtitute of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leif, &amp; left to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; run into miſcheifs, they proſper not, they play the vnthrifts, they ſpend all, they continue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, &amp; honeſt roome, and reporte which their fathers had, we are not to thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is any fault in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe of God or defecte in his prouidence but rather we are to aſſure our ſelues, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtacie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteps of their good father hath pluckt vpon them that iuſt plague which their ſins haue deſerued, &amp; ſo are the authors of their own deſtruction. A third regard there is alſo to be had in this matter, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; vnſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of our iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for we many times are deceiued in our opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for iuſt &amp; righteous which is not ſo in deed: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> want of perfect knowledg in this caſe, we are caried away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> main cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of falſe ſentences, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doubt &amp; diſtruſt in
<pb facs="tcp:20078:32"/>
the promiſe of God. Therefore wee are to ſet a watch before our heartes, and to keepe the doore of our lippes taking heede howe, and what we doe thinke and pronounce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeede and poſteritie of men, and the ſtate of their fathers: for many a man haue been taken for honeſt, zealous, well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, a good Goſpeller, &amp; a man vpright in his actions who neuertheleſſe hath played the hypocrite in all theſe things, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a viſor before his face to blinde the eyes, and to abuſe the iudgments of the world: ſo that it is no marueile, that wheras we tooke him for a man of great integritie and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, being in our opinions deceiued, his iſſue and generation after him tracing in the ſame ſteppes of hypocriſie and iniquitie with their fathers, are viſited with the ſharpe rod of the Lordes indignation, growing into ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, impotencie, beggery, and ſuch like miſeries, the fruites and reapings of their owne diſſolute ſowing. Ye ſee then how the wordes of the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> are to be taken &amp; how the poore man is therhence to collect, and applie to his ſicke conſcience, his ſalue of comfort. Let him content himſelfe with his lowe degree: let him ſerue the Lorde in pureneſſe of ſpirite, let him relye in al things
<pb facs="tcp:20078:32"/>
vpon his good prouidence and according to his habilitie prouide for the good education of his children, and then let him commit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Lorde, and commend his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to his protection: hee giueth to beaſtes their foode,<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.9.</note> and to the young Rauens their ſuſtenance. The fowles of the heauen that ſowe not, reape not,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.26.</note> and carry not into any barnes are fedde by your heauenly father. The Lillies of the fielde doe ſpring, and are clothed in ſuch ſort, that <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his glorie was not arayed like one of them, how much more will he cloth, and feede you, your wiues, your children, your familie, your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie for euer, if yee bee not like Gentiles without faith, but like good Chriſtians with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out immoderate thought, not as thoſe whoſe whole delight is ſeated and planted, in Mammon which is riches, and made ſo drunken with the pleaſures of ſinne, that God and all godlineſſe is quite forgotten, and out of minde, but as thoſe that firſt of al ſeeke his kingdome and the righteouſneſſe thereof, to whome there is this ſweet and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler promiſe made, by him in whoſe mouth there was neuer found guile,<note place="margin">Verſe. 33.</note> that all other neceſſaries whatſoeuer belonging to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, of our bodies, and natures ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:20078:33"/>
by him ſufficiently prouided, and miniſtred aboundantly for our vſe, and comfort. Yt will not be amiſſe in this matter for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the poore man, &amp; his better induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to contentation and ioy, to goe a little farther, and to conſider how much his eſtate is commended in the courſe of the ſcripture, and preferred before the ſtate of the riche man. For I aſſure you for any thing that I can read to the contrary, that the qualitie of a low degree being in many places co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with the condition of a rich man, the firſt by reaſon of ſome ſpeciall aduantages which it carieth, receiueth moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier place, and better commendation then the other. I will not ſtand vpon this point, that it pleaſed the ſonne of God Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to make choyſe of a poore eſtate vpon earth, rather then of a riche, and of an eſtate ſo poore, as that by his own confeſſion, the Foxes had holes, and the birdes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen had neſts,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.20. 2. Cor. 8.9.</note> but he himſelf had not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to reſt his head, ſo that in his perſon wee may ſee and finde the condition of pouertie ſanctified vnto vs, and not in him onely but in his Apoſtles alſo, who left and forſooke al that they had, and followed him, inſomuch that <hi>Peters</hi> particuler ſong to the creeple,<note place="margin">Acts. 3.6.</note> might haue beene ſonge of all of them, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:33"/>
and golde haue I none, the obſeruation of which point might ſerue ſomewhat to the matter, but I will leaue examples, which doe rather beautifie then prooue, and record that which is expreſſed, as taught, &amp; commaunded by Chriſt, ſeruing very fitly to the purpoſe, in a place of <hi>Mathew,</hi> where he directing a certayne young man a courſe to grow to a perfection in the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wiſhed him to goe and make ſale of all that he had, and giue it to the poore,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> and to come &amp; folow him. By which words we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how the ſtate of pouertie was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt vnto him, as a better trade, &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſſeſſion of great la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, which then he retayned. I will not ſay that this is a thing neceſſarily belonging to our time, and that the precept or counſell there giuen by Chriſt to the yong man is general, as binding vs &amp; others now to the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, as thoughe, that without the ſale of our goods and the vndertaking of a voluntary pouertie, noe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might performe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſure of feare &amp; ſeruice which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, for ſo ſay our aduerſaries,<note place="margin">Caniſius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſ. titul. de concil. fol. <hi>336.</hi>
                  </note> but I know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame direction was ſpeciall for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, &amp; perſonal for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe inward diſeaſe Chriſt ſearched, &amp; touched by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining a rule or pattern of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:20078:34"/>
loue, which he was to looke into, and to frame himſelf accordingly, who before brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of that ſufficiencie and full obedience which was not in him, had lyed egregiouſly to Chriſt, in affirming that he had kept al the commaundements of the ſecond table from his youth and lackt nothing, whereof hee was immediately in the preſence of Chriſt at that time conuicted, being ſo farre from the practiſe of any ſuch perfect and abſolute loue, as that vpon the ſpeech of Chriſt. he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted heauie and ſorowfull, becauſe he had great poſſeſſions: whereby he apparantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed, how many leagues he was of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a conſummate obedience, in that he preferred his couetouſe affection, before the loue that he falſely pretended to carry towardes his neighbour. But although the ſame directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reached for that time to him onely and perticulerly, yet I doubt not but the ſame may ſerue now as a peculier rule, for ſuch a one as ſhalbe founde culpable in the ſame fault, and offend in the ſame error with him. But ſuppoſe not, yet my collection is probable, that the two ſeuerall conditions of pouertie, and riches being there ſette one againſt another in that young man, the firſt in regarde of the profite of the man, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="tcp:20078:34"/>
before the latter: for otherwiſe to what ende ſerueth that ſame conſequent iudgment of Chriſt vpon the ſight of that young mans behauiour, pronounced to his diſciples, and that with an aſſeueration. Verely I ſay vnto you, that a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdome of heauen, and the Euangeliſt <hi>Marke</hi> reporteth the ſpeech to haue beene deliuered in maner of admiration,<note place="margin">Marke. 10.23.</note> how hardly doe they that haue riches enter into the kingdome of God? mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning that the very poſſeſſing of riches is ſuch a pulbacke or rather plague vnto a man, as that it keepeth him from ſuch good actions, and Chriſtian courſes, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not being in that ſorte burdened, hee might cheerefully performe and proſecute with delight, for the diſcharge of thoſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall duties, whereunto he is bound by the word and lawe of God. And yet this is not al that is there vttered by Chriſt to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but hee proceedeth further and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the matter not onely hard but impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo that a riche man ſhoulde bee ſaued: inſomuch that the paſſage for a Camel through the eye of a nedle is eaſier and more poſſible, then the entrance of a riche man into the kingdome of God. A harde
<pb facs="tcp:20078:35"/>
ſpeech I confeſſe, and yet the ſpeech of him whoſe truth &amp; knowledge may not be called in queſtion, being himſelf the very truth, but ye may ſay to me, as the diſciples ſaid then vnto Chriſt, being exceedingly amazed at the wordes, who can then bee ſaued: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſuch as are not in mind proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor in qualitie like to that poore man, from whom the occaſion of this ſpeech grew and was taken, for I acknowledge that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches it ſelfe conſidered ſimplie, are the good creatures of God, and in their nature they are not euill, but commodious, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diuers wayes: but in that place Chriſt indeede ſpeaketh of ſuch rich men, as in their wealth are idolaters,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.6.</note> for which things ſake the wrath of God commeth vpon the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſobedience: ſuch as incline their hearts not to the teſtimonies of God but to couete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.36.</note> making their gold their very God, not by profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by a kind of curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence planted therin. And the truth of this approueth by the former place of <hi>Marke,</hi> where it is euident that Chriſt ſpeaketh of ſuch as put their truſt in their riches,<note place="margin">Marke 10.24.</note> the very ſame wordes being there expreſly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. So that not riches but coueteouſneſſe is heere condemned as the thing that produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb facs="tcp:20078:35"/>
an impoſſibilitie for an entrance to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and as it were a barre and obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that keepeth faſt the doore opening a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the kingdome of God. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ye ſee, how that Chriſt in that place of <hi>Mathew</hi> although hee taxeth onely that groſſe ſinne which dependeth vpon riches, yet he pronounceth the difficultie or impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie againſt the riche man without any ſpeciall limitation: becauſe indeed we are ſo peruerſe in hearte, and in nature ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> without an extraordinary grace, and gouernment, it is impoſſible that we ſhould not preſume of our wealth, and waxe proud thereof, and forget God and ſo runne into thoſe miſcheifs, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whirlepoole wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort of rich men are miſerably plunged. For we ſee what the vniuerſall caſe almoſt of all our riche men is, hauing their thoughts eſtrainged from God, and all loue of godlineſſe baniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hearts: being ſet out in colours in the perſon of that rich man, the parable of whom is knowen of al his kinſmen, but his ſin is auoyded of few of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: who vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> large increaſe of his fruits:<note place="margin">Luke. 2.16.</note> and the plenteouſe bleſſing of his groundes, did not diſpoſe himſelf to returne the duty of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to god for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, but applied his
<pb facs="tcp:20078:36"/>
heart to the delight, and pleaſure therereof, being occupied with care for the amplifying of his barnes, &amp; the gathering of his goods, and the procuring of the eaſe of his ſoule, to eate and drinke, and take paſtime not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering in whoſe hands and power that ſoule of his reſted, who for the abuſe of his plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp; prophane ſecuritie pluckt the ſame from him, when he thought himſelf far from any ſuch plague or perill. This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte image and mirror of the moſt rich men of our time, who being depriued of all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and Chriſtian ſenſe, and wholy poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a ſpirit of carnall greedineſſe, ſeeke onely the things of the world, coueting to be rich in themſelues,<note place="margin">Verſe 21.</note> but not in God, vſing all vnlawfull practiſes, and vngodly pollicies, to hale, and pull corruptible pelfe into their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, wherby they bewray themſelues to be no better then greedie dogs, as the prophet ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Eſay 56.11.</note> which thinke that they haue neuer enough. And from this filthy fountayne, ſprings the foule ſtreames of their irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liues, their proud co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits, their voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſires, their prophane epicuriſme, their brutiſh forgetfulneſſe of God, his honor, his word, &amp; their own duties euery way. Let vs looke for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtate perticulerly of
<pb facs="tcp:20078:36"/>
our own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey &amp; take a view of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe of life in thoſe who amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs ſit in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt roomes, &amp; by reaſon of their welth, beare the ſtroke in gouernment, and other matters, where ſhal we find more Atheiſme, barbarouſneſſe, confuſion, looſeneſſe, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſacrilege, and what you will elſe then among them? For their owne parte they thinke that they maye ſinne by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie being as men not ſubiect to the checkes or controlements of any, their lykings bee lawes, and their wils reaſons: and as they them ſelues liue without lawe, ſo doe their families without order: their houſes being not lodgings for Chriſtians, but harbours for Sauages: not exerciſed with anie one point of good diſcipline, or pietie: but ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtande as monuments of miſrule, and ſpectacles of all kinde of lewdneſſe: their children fed, but not taught: their ſeruants and retinue, as farre from the feare of God, and the fruites thereof, yea from humane ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie, as they are neere to the contempt of God, the irreuerence of his worde, and the diſhonour of his name by their common ſwearings, and blaſphemies. And I woulde to God that this were the fault onely of the Libertines of our age, who carrie no note
<pb facs="tcp:20078:37"/>
at all, nor marke in the matter of zeale and ſinceritie, but this abuſe, &amp; ouerſight (which may iuſtly prouoke teares,) is crept within the doores and roofes of ſuch as make greate ſhew of religion, &amp; are reputed of the number of the beſt Profeſſors, and fauourers, whoſe houſes are not in ſuch ſort purged &amp; reformed from theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon corruptions, as in ſoule I wiſh, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in conſcience are bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Which thing I take to be moſt requiſite for their conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; moſt worthy of their chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attendance &amp; carefulnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo al ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks of offence, &amp; occaſions of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our common cauſe may bee remoued, wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy that ſpeaketh euill of vs as of euil doers,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> may by our good works which he ſhal ſee, glorify God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of viſitation, ſo that I hope you now conceiue by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the ful ſenſe &amp; reaſon of the former al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation or ſpeech of Chriſt, pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing the impoſſibility of entrance into the kingdome of God againſt the rich man, ſtanding in the difficultie of applying himſelfe, by occaſion of his wealth, to the practiſe of good things: and in the impediments which doe accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the poſſeſſion of riches, withholding a man from the free courſe of chriſtian duties, &amp; obedience, which otherwiſe he might in good
<pb facs="tcp:20078:37"/>
meaſure yeelde himſelfe vnto, the experience whereof is very large, and plentiful amongſt vs, foraſmuch as wee finde not one riche man almoſt amongeſt a hundred wel giuen, religious, zealous, a louer of the trueth, a regarder of his ſoule, and ſaluation, more then of his luſte and pleaſure, but from the leaſt of them to the greateſt,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.13.</note> with one minde and conſent they drawe after co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneeſſe, following the way of <hi>Caine,</hi> &amp; caſt away by the deceite of <hi>Baalams</hi> wages:<note place="margin">Iude 11.</note> ſo that wee may runne to and fro by our ſtreetes, as by the ſtreetes of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 5.1.5.</note> in the dayes of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and ſeeke and enquire in our open places if there bee any one man amongſt our great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that executeth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſeeketh the trueth, but wee ſhall not finde him: they haue altogether bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the yoke, and burſt the bondes, and haue not knowen the iudgement of the Lorde, ſo that in this caſe I cannot reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our time better, then to the time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt liued, wherein the myſteries of the kingdome of God, were hid from the wiſe &amp; prudent, and men of vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.25.</note> and were opened to the ſimple yea vnto babes, and wherein the great men, the princes, the Scribes, and the Phariſees, and the richer
<pb facs="tcp:20078:38"/>
ſorte deſpiſed Chriſt, and counted the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching fooliſhnes but the poore by his owne teſtimonie,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.5.</note> and triall receiued the Goſpel, &amp; were not offended in him. I will not here (although good occaſion is offered) enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a rehearſall of the common ſpeeches of our great worldlings, and Atheiſtes, who ſwelling with pride, and almoſt renting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder with diſdaine and rancour, becauſe of the libertie of the Goſpel, and the paſſage of the word (maugre their hearts &amp; beards,) doe breake out into that ſame wicked aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of the Phariſees to their officers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt: who beeing amazed at the grace of his woordes, and ſtricken in their heartes with the efficacie of his doctrines, were ſo farre from doing violence vnto him, as the high Prieſts had commaunded them, as that contrariwiſe they bare witnes of his power, and confeſſed the excellencie of his ſayings, affirming, that neuer man ſpake as he did.<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.46.47</note> But what ſaid the Phariſees? are yee alſo deceiued? doe anie of the rulers or of the Phariſees beleeue in him? but this people that knowe not the lawe are curſed: theſe are the very formall words of the looſe liuers of this time, who of purpoſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace as much as they can the Preachers of
<pb facs="tcp:20078:38"/>
the worde, and to diminiſhe the glory of the Goſpel if they coulde, doe vſually make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons betwixt the baſe condition of ſuch as are louers of the trueth, and diligent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the worde preached, and the high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of thoſe that make a mocke of Chriſt, and apply themſelues to the perſecuting of him in his ſaintes and members: looke (ſay they) what a ſort of beggerly, and poore fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes doe follow him, ſuch as haue ſcarce a peece of ſiluer in their purſes, or of bread in their houſes, they are his diſciples, and are become great holy folkes, and will ſhortly proue Preachers, and proceed Doctors: but who of vs doe fancie him? doe not wee that bee Gentlemen, rich men, rulers, and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſpeake euill of the man: doe not wee report the woorſt we can of him, among our ſelues, and to ſtrangers: doe not wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne his pulpit talke, make a ieſt of his threatnings, and preferre accuſations, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and billes of enditements againſt him? there are none of vs that doe loue him, and therefore both hee, and they that heare him are deceiued and accurſed. Thus the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees of our time deale with vs, and ſhewe themſelues as it weee in print, to bee ſuch maner of men as were the Iewes, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20078:39"/>
hearts vpon the hearing of <hi>Stephens</hi> words braſt for anger,<note place="margin">Act. 7.54.</note> and whoſe teeth gnaſhed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: and ſuch alſo, as were the Prieſts, and captayne of the Temple, and Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> who being not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues, by reaſon of the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirite wherewith they were poſſeſſed becauſe that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> did ſuche, and ſuche thinges in their miniſterie,<note place="margin">Act. 4.1.2.</note> they came vppon them and tooke it grieuouſly, that they taught the people, and preached in the name of Ieſus the reſurrection from the dead, but they are condemned by their owne mouthes as euill ſeruauntes, diſclayming from the loue, and knowledge of that thing, and of thoſe men, who ought to bee their ioye,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> and pleaſure, and would bee a ſauour of life vnto life in them, if they were ordayned to ſaluation. Wee confeſſe that in externall braueries, and in the glorie of fleſhe, and pompe of the worlde they exceede and goe beyonde vs, but this is not a thing that maye breede a iuſt offence in anie of vs, foraſmuche as the cauſe of fayth and religion, doeth not hang vppon the ſleeues, and authoritye of men, neither doth conſiſt in multitude nor in the degrees of perſons, but the ſame is
<pb facs="tcp:20078:39"/>
to be iudged by the eternal and immutable worde of God, which is the word of trueth,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.5.</note> of life, of ſaluation, of reconciliation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, the onely rule &amp; direction of the faithful: ſo that although the heathen do rage, and the people murmure, the kings of the earth band themſelues, and the princes do aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet all this may bee againſt the Lorde, and againſt his Chriſt, with purpoſe to caſt off the yoke of his ſeruice,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2.3.</note> and to breake the band of their obedience, for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is no priuiledge for trueth, neither is gentilitie, any warrant for godlines. The true wiſedome of God, which is the Goſpel was not known of any of the Princes of the worlde, for had they knowen it,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.8</note> they would not haue crucified the Lorde of glorie. And therefore albeit in number we be few, in eſtate poore, and in byrth not Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yet in the knowledge of God wee may be noble, in faith riche,<note place="margin">Iames 2.5.</note> and in the ſight of God as precious as the honorable. Yea, in this matter the caſe doth ſo ſtande, that for the moſt parte thoſe thinges, which to the eyes of the worlde ſeeme moſt excellent, and by the iudgement of man are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and preferred, are notwithſtanding ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of the Lorde, whoſe eyes beholde,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:40"/>
not the face and legges, but doth pearce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reynes: and ſo likewiſe on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, thoſe thinges which in the opinion of men are vile and of no eſtimation, are neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe in high account before God. For hee ſeeth not as man ſeeth,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.7.</note> for man looketh on the outward appearance, but hee beholdeth the heart, ſo ſaide the Lorde himſelfe to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> being deceiued in the faire complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and high ſtature of <hi>Eliab,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Iſhaie.</hi> It is a notable ſentence of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in his Prouerbes to this purpoſe, Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the poore that walketh in his vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.6.</note> then hee that peruerteth his wayes though he be riche, and againe, a poore man is better then a lyer, meaning that although a man be deſtitute of riches, and yet doeth poſſeſſe, and practiſe vertue, he is to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med aboue that man, which hauing much wealth, yet ſtands voide of all honeſtie, ſo that if there were nothing elſe but this one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good thing following the eſtate of the poore man, yet it might bee a fufficient mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to prouoke him to the ioye, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing which <hi>Iames</hi> doeth here ſet before him, becauſe the feare of God, and obedience to his trueth doeth not conſiſt in golde, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, in many poſſeſſions &amp; noble progenies,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:40"/>
but in a regenerated ſpirite, and in a heart purified by faith. Which ſpirite &amp; heart, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee may plentifully be adorned with, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the externall things of the world, hee bee not ſo full as others, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he ſhould paſſe his time with teares, and ſeparate all comfort from his heart, the bleſſed Apoſtle affirming for his conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the kingdome of God is not meate nor drinke, nor any ſuch outward things,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> but righteouſnes, and peace, and ioy in the holie Ghoſt: and foraſmuch alſo as by the ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his condition, and the abſence of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, being the very chaynes and fetters of the minde, he may more quietly apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the ſeruice of God, and runne the courſe of righteouſneſſe, tending to the gate of Gods kingdome more promptly then the rich man, who by reaſon of the loade of his wealth, is ſo preſſed with care, and priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with carnall cogitations, as that hee hardely can diſpoſe himſelfe accordingly, therefore the man is the ſooner, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to content himſelfe with his poore, but profitable ſtate, and not either by griefe to torment himſelfe, or by a hungry humor to couet that thing, which may bring with it more trouble then quietnes, and more diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage
<pb facs="tcp:20078:41"/>
then commoditie if he make price of the ſweet freedome of his conſcience. A very reuerend,<note place="margin">Muſcul. in Math. cap. 21. fol. 490.</note> and learned <hi>Diuine</hi> of this latter age, diſputing of purpoſe concerning this matter, ſetteth downe briefly diuers ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall thinges wherein the ſtate of the poore man, is more happie and fortunate then the condition of the riche, which although at the firſt bluſhe it maye ſeeme to bee ſomewhat ſtraunge, becauſe wee ſee how euerie man contendeth to auoyde and flee from the doore of pouertie, as from a Scorpion, and is as vnwilling to come neere it, as a marriner is loth to approche a rocke in the ſea for feare of ſhipwracke, yet vppon a ſober and prudent balancing of the differences, it wil appeare howe probable, and reaſonable the matter is, and that howeſoeuer men doe followe their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and greedie appetites in coueting to bee riche, yet when they haue done all that they can in that reſpect, they muſt ſaye with <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 2.11.</note> that it is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and vexation of the ſpirite, and iumpe in iudgement with this diuine, to preferre the poore mans vnhappineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their owne bliſſe. For yee ſhall ſee. The poore man is not ſo muche intangled
<pb facs="tcp:20078:41"/>
with the cares of the worlde, and deceite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of riches, as the other is,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.22.</note> which are expreſſely called thornes by Chriſt, becauſe in many they do ſuffocate or choake the good ſeede of the worde, and makes them altogether vnfruitefull: the rich man hee is in mynde troubled, in bodie buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in his thoughtes diſtracted, hee hath ſo manie farmes to viſite, ſo manie yoke of Oxen to looke vnto, ſo manie bargaynes to make, ſo muche money to paye, and to receyue, and ſo many thinges to doe, as that hee can ſpare no time to regarde the ſtate of his ſoule, nor ſpende an houre to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide his ſpirituall wealth, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, by the hearing of the woorde of GOD, the meanes of his ſaluation prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and if he doe by chance come to a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at any time, it were as good, or rather better hee were abſent: for although his bodie bee in the Churche, yet his wits run vppon his buſineſſe, and his ſenſes are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about other matters, the voyce of the Preacher is as an vnperfect ſounde to his eares: hee receiueth the beginning of a ſentence, but attendes not the latter end: he heares the latter end, but hath forgotten the beginning, and ſo it comes to paſſe, that as
<pb facs="tcp:20078:42"/>
he came to the temple with litle deuotion, ſo he returnes home with little profite, but the poore man is at libertie in reſpect of theſe thinges, his minde is not in ſuch ſorte fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled, nor his wits with ſuch cares trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but with a free minde, and conſcience prepared with the feare of God, he doeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelfe to his ſeruice, deſiring to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in knowledge and in all good things, holding nothing ſo precious, as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his duetie in that caſe, the glorie of God, and the Chriſtian care of his owne ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Againe, the riche man is Couſine germane to <hi>Diues</hi> the glutton, who as hee was full in his purſe, ſo he would needes bee delicious in his fare: his wealth and his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et muſt bee correſpondent,<note place="margin">Luke 16.19.</note> he muſt eate and drinke of the beſt, his table muſt bee furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with all the delicate meates, and drinks that may be gotten for money, making his bellie his God, and planting a felicitie in the varietie of meates, and drinks, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of diſhes. And heere hence growe the inconueniences and miſchiefes of ſurfeting, drunkenneſſe, wantonnes, concupiſcences, and idleneſſe the mother of all wickedneſſe, for the bellie being full, the bones looke for
<pb facs="tcp:20078:42"/>
reſt, and not of this onelie, but of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the bodie alſo, as the Goute, and drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, with others of the like nature, the fruits of ſuperfluous, and immoderate feeding. But nowe the poore man as hee cannot by reaſon of his wantes, ſo he doth not acquaint himſelfe with ſuch a gluttonous kind of life: he contentes his nature with a little, and therefore hath his body ſound, his mind vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, his limmes ſtrong for labour, his legges proportionable, and by reaſon of his good courſe, liueth long, and dieth in a good age, which is the bleſſing of God, whereas the gorged riche man doeth by his intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance abbreuiate the continuance of his own life, and ſo committes a greate ſinne in the breach of the ſixt commaundement of the lawe.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.13</note>
               </p>
               <p>Further, the poore man by reaſon of his daylie labour, and ordinarie trauell in his vocation, doth ſo weaken the forces &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his bodie for the time, as that in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening, and houre of reſt, he refreſheth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with great pleaſure, hauing that ſweet comfort of nature which is ſleepe, as it were at his commandement: whereby he is ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently reuiued, that in the morning he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth againe to his common buſines, freſh,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:43"/>
luſtie, ioyfull, and fit for his worke, whereas the riche man is in this point like to <hi>Ahaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueroſh</hi> the king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> of whom we read in the booke of <hi>Heſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſt. 6.1.</note> who could not ſleepe in the night, and therefore called for the booke of the Records, or Chronicles of the lande, that by peruſing of them, hee might driue out the time of the night: our riche men conſider not that it pleaſeth GOD manye times for a puniſhment to them to withholde his benefite of natural ſleepe from their eyes, the ſame being a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall gifte of his, for the preſeruation of our nature, which otherwiſe without the ſame could not poſſibly indure. The firſt man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> coulde not ſleepe of himſelfe vntill the Lord cauſed it to fall vpon him,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.21.</note> as ſhewing thereby that it is in his hands either to giue it or not to giue it, to ſend it or to withdraw it as pleaſeth him. And therefore in the vſe of his iuſtice, he doth many times depriue the riche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this comfort, ſuffering them to lye toſſing, &amp; tumbling vpon their beds, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring this ordinary refreſhing, but cannot haue it, and I my ſelfe haue hearde many of them complayning of the want thereof, that they paſſe many nightes, with little or no ſleepe at al, taking the ſame to come by ſome
<pb facs="tcp:20078:43"/>
happe or fortune, by the length of the night, or ſome ſtirre and noyce, not conſidering the iuſtice of God afflicting them in that ſorte with vnreſt in the night, to put them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ill ſpending of the day, which thing being regarded of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 5.11.</note> made him to affirme, that the ſleepe of him that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth is ſweete, whether hee eate little or muche, but the ſatietie of the riche will not ſuffer him to ſleepe, and againe, the hearte of ſuche a man taketh no reſt in the night.<note place="margin">Ib. 2.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, the poore man, by reaſon of the perpetuall neceſſities of his life, is ſo well accuſtomed with common afflictions, as hunger, loſſe, diſpleaſure, iniuries, want of money and ſuche like thinges, as that it is no trouble nor diſquietneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, when he is in any ſuch ſort pinched, becauſe his youth, and age, and all the dayes of his life hath beene nothing els but as it were a ſchoole of diſcipline, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of tryall to him, and therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer croſſe happeneth, hee doeth endure it with patience, and vndergoe it with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation, beyng well pleaſed with his lot, but the rich man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath bin acquainted with no ſuch croſſes, hauing liued in eaſe, wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:44"/>
friendſhippe, proſperitie, quietneſſe, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight, and therefore not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what affliction meaneth, when he by the hand of God is neuer ſo little touched, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be with an iniurie, enemies, hunger, loſſe of children, landes, or wealth he is by &amp; by carried away beyonde the limites of all reaſonable patience, he fretteth, and fumeth and taketh on like a madde man, yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fometh out blaſphemies againſt God, and complaineth of the harde dealing of God towardes him, as though God were bound by the receite of ſome benefite of his, to extend alwayes the partes of loue &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie for ſhew of thankfulneſſe: and ſo thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that God ſhoulde ſtill let him liue in ſuch a flouriſhing ſtate, as ſomtimes he did, when he feeles but a ſmal alteration, though it be but a gentle admonition, he takes it in no good part, he growes outragious, &amp; will not be perſwaded to any moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mind: ſo that it is impoſſible that the ſinguler ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of patience ſhould poſſeſſe his ſoule: but the poore man is prepared for euery occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, come what affliction or aduerſitie will come it is no newes to him, ſeeing the whole courſe of his life, hath been a practiſe of bearing and ſuffering.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20078:44"/>Laſtly the poore man hauing liued in his ſimple eſtate with a good conſcience caried in all his actions, when the time commeth that hee muſt pay his due to nature, and goe the way of all fleſh, death which is common to al, is welcome to him: hee hath no great wil or teſtament to make, no goods gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by vſury, and opreſſion to reſtore, no maſſe of money to leaue behinde him, no ſtore of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to breede in him a hatred of death, but knowing that the ſame is his port of reſt, and concluſion of all ſorowes, he receiues it qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly ioyfully, and Chriſtianly. But oh what a terror to the mind of the riche man is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of death, howe many greeuous ſinnes hath he marching before him, which makes him to abhorre the ende of his life: the reſpect of his former felicitie in this world, his wife, his wealth, his place, his cofers, his lands, his houſes, his ſeruants, euery of theſe perticulers miniſters a thouſand occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of deſiring life to his heart, and as he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth loath to dye, ſo hee knowes not howe to prepare himſelfe for the ſame, but many times it comes ſo to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath paſſed all his life in ſinne, and ſecuritie, and vanitie without a diſcharge of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God and the worlde, is by the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:45"/>
iuſtice of God ſo farre from repentance, and a Chriſtian ende, as that what with carnall cares, and hope of longer continuance, and other things of the like qualitie, wherof Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan at that time will powre in plentie, and ſufficient number into his head and braines, he ſhall haue no remembrance of making an attonement betwixt God, and his ſoule, but ſhall die deſperately without hope of mercie, and impenitently without remorſe for his ſinne: this point of difference in the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the rich and poore man is notably touched by the ſonne of <hi>Sirachi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 41.1.2.</note> who in one verſe cryeth out, O death how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liueth at reſt in his poſſeſſions, vnto the man that hath nothing to vexe him, &amp; that hath proſperitie in all things. But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next verſe he proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, O death how acceptable is thy iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the needy vnto him whoſe ſtrength fayleth, and is vexed with all thinges, &amp;c. Whereby is prooued, that good reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning death that the poore man ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, being glad when the ende of his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries approcheth: but contrariwiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horror, and feare of death, which poſſeſſeth the mind of the rich man, who can in no caſe abide to heare ſpeech of the ſame, being the thing that amongſt all things elſe hee leaſt broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:45"/>
&amp; moſt abhorreth. Now all theſe things being conſidered I referre the iudgment to your ſelues, which of theſe two is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er man: the rich with ſo many inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences attending his perſon, or the poore with ſo many aduantages accompanying his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue paſt your verdit, then apply it to the preſent wordes of <hi>Iames</hi> for the ſtrengthning of his direction of ioy to the poore man: for I doubte not but that the dililigent obſeruation of theſe differences, as it cannot but breed in the riche man a kinde of diſliking of himſelfe, and his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo it cannot but ingender in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an allowance, &amp; approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his pouertie, &amp; ſo cauſe him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more willingly to practiſe ioy &amp; contentation in the manifolde diſtreſſes of this life. But now by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way if for your ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction you aſke me this neceſſary queſtion, what maner of poore men I ſpeak of al this while, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e what doubtful, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are diuers perſons, going vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name &amp; title of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, who by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their lewd, &amp; wicked courſe of life deſerue no iot of theſe good ſpeeches, but rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whip &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, &amp; al maner of diſgrace, being ſuch as are vnworthy in any good place to be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred or ſpoken of: I wil ſhortly reſolue you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20078:46"/>
that by the poore man I doe not vnderſtand the idle begger, and rogiſh companion, who not applying himſelfe to any ordinary la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, makes a profeſſion of beggery, and liues altogether vpon the ſpoyle: ſuch both by the lawe of God, and the commendable lawes of this realme prouided in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, are to be puniſhed according to the meaſure of their idleneſſe, and qualitie of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond liuing: neither doe I meane by the poore man ſuch maner of perſons, as are common haunters of alehouſes, vnthriftes, ſpendals, and drunkards, hauing ſcarce ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pennie in their purſes or coate to their ſhoulders, and yet all the weeke long lye at ſuch tipling places, hauing no regard for a ciuill behauiour, nor deſire to purchaſe an honeſt &amp; good report amongſt men. Which ſpecial thing I could wiſh by ſome ſeuere or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der might be reformed in this place, wherin there are many offendors in this caſe, the negligent conſideration whereof is occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many riots and breaches of the lawe in many poynts (and of much ſinne alſo) but by the poore man I meane ſuch a one as in ſcripture by the ſpirit of God is commended vnto vs, and committed to our regarde, the man vpon whom it hath pleaſed God not to
<pb facs="tcp:20078:46"/>
beſtow ſo great a portion of riches as vpon others for ſome ſecrete purpoſe of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, being no tall Cedar, no man of great office or authoritie in the common wealth, but an artificer or handicraftes man, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diligently in his manuarie trade or ſcience, to releeue himſelfe, and maintayne his familie thereby, demeaning himſelfe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly as a chriſtian, and quietly like a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in the feare of God, and according to the qualitie of his vocation, ſuch a one in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I take to be ment by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a poore man. As for our roges, and vagabonds I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them out of the role, and number of poore men, commended by the ſpirit of God, and ſpoken of by vs, who becauſe they do not labour, they ſhould not eate, &amp; I could wiſh for them alſo, that by the good execution of our lawes, the countrey might be rid of the burden and charge of them, who by the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and diligence of the officers ought to be taken and ſent to our bridewelles, and mill-houſes erected for the purpoſe, that ſo by iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice they might bee driuen to that paynes and amendment of life which of themſelues they purpoſe not to practiſe. Within this compaſſe of poore men we may include thoſe alſo, vpon whoſe ſhoulders it hath pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:20078:47"/>
God to lay the croſſe of pouertie for their triall or puniſhment: hauing beene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in very ſufficient ſtate, and able both to liue of themſelues, and to releeue others in neceſſitie, but now by ſome caſualitie, are decayed, and come behinde hand, and fallen into pouertie, as either by fire, robbing, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, ſureteſhip or ſuch like occaſions, and therefore are compelled to relye vpon a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall charitie, with whom we may in like ſort ioyne the poore of our almes houſes, the olde, lame, blinde, maymed ſouldier, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch impotent perſons, to whom there are promiſes made of farre better ſtates, if for the time they can reſolue themſelues to heare of their miſeries w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſhoulder of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to truſt to the good prouidence of God expecting a time of helpe and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from him. And as theſe men are in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places of ſcripture perſwaded to quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and contentation, ſo here by the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> they are prouoked to reioycing, to caſt off all mourning and complaining, and all partes of impatiencie, to conſider the commodities of their lowe degree, to looke vp to the heigth and excellencie of Gods kingdome prepared for them, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the mercies of God, to giue him
<pb facs="tcp:20078:47"/>
thankes without grudging for his viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo to liue, as that by their pouertie, God may accordingly be glorified, and their afflicted bodies, and ſoules in the ende ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: of which matter ye ſhall heare more (if God permitte) the next time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:20078:48"/>
               <head>The third Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce in that he is exalted.</hi> It is nothing ſtraunge that <hi>Iames</hi> ſhoulde heere giue counſell to the poore man to reioyce in his pouertie, or rather in his exaltation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lorde by the prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> doth reſtrayne,<note place="margin">Ier. 9.23.24.</note> and limite al reioycing, and glorying to the knowledge, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his will: ſaying, let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, nor the rich man in his riches ches, but let him that glorieth, glorie in that he vnderſtandeth and knoweth me: and our Sauiour would not giue libertie to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 10.20.</note> to reioyce becauſe the diuels were ſubdued to them in his name, but rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their owne names were written in heauen: and the bleſſed Apoſtle alſo woulde not diſpoſe of himſelf to reioyce in any thing, but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as himſelfe profeſſeth to the <hi>Galatians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galat. 6.14.</note> which places ouerthrow not the wordes of <hi>Iames</hi> here, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture is not as a houſe or kingdome deuided in it ſelfe, but as God is alwayes one, and he neuer contrary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:48"/>
for his worde alſo is one, and that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer iarres with it ſelfe. A generall rule for all our ioy is giuen by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.31.</note> ſaying, he that reioyceth let him reioyce in the Lord: which rule if it doth ſquare out, and meaſure the vſe of our mirth, and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then whatſoeuer ſpeciall thing it be that we do reioyce in, or of, it can but be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in it ſelfe, and acceptable to God: for the ioye of the faithfull is not in ſuch force tyed vp as it were by the winges, in reſpects of the receite of the graces of God, but that there is this ſcope giuen them, that looke howe many good bleſſings they are made partakers of from God, of ſo many they may freely, and without ſume be glad, and ioyful, prouided alwayes that the rule be kepte, to make God the foundation of their ioye, and in the vſe thereof to haue regard of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the benefite, and the prayſe of his name. If we ſearch the ſcriptures &amp; peruſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories of the Church, we ſhall read of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things from whence the godly in al ages haue taken occaſion to reioyce: as of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance of the faithfull, out of the hands of perſecutors, victory againſt the enemies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from captiuitie, the free courſe of the Goſpell, the obedience and conſtancie of the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:49"/>
brethren, the gouernment of a good prince, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peace of conſcience vpon feeling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercie of God, &amp; many other things, which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers if they happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs, as they haue of old to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God, we may in like ſort, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce reioyce in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they haue done. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hereby all the carnall reioycings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, who many times boaſt of their ſin, &amp; triumph in doing euill, making not God, but Sathan whom they ſerue the foundation of their ioye: for when the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are in ſome diſtreſſe, and any way afflicted, then as <hi>Tyrus</hi> reioyced at the ouerthrow of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 26.2.</note> ſaying, a hathe gate of the citie is broken, it is turned vnto mee, for ſeeing ſhe is deſolate I ſhalbe reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, ſo do the wicked <hi>Tyrians</hi> of al times clap their hands &amp; are well apaid when they ſee the miſeries of the righteous thinking the ſight of their calamitie, to be a ſufficient cauſe and reaſon for their execrable melody. The proofe whereof is great, and large euen amongſt vs, ſeeing it can not be denied, but that there are ſuch ſcoffing mates, and riming marchants, as were in the dayes of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who made ſongs of his trouble, &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed in his aduerſitie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.15.16.</note> and ſaid, a ha, a ha, our eyes haue ſeen the man ouerthrowen, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20078:49"/>
theſe perſons, when they ſee neuer ſo little trouble raiſed vp againſt vs, that we are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, cited, ſuſpended, excommunicated, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dighted, inhibited, and in ſuch like ſort diuers wayes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, they cry out there, there, ſo we would haue it, they make feaſtes one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in token of ioy, and looke bigge vpon vs, as if they would deuoure vs, yea they deale as the <hi>Phariſies</hi> ſometimes dealt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mark. 14.11.</note> who when they heard that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Iſcariot</hi> woulde betray him into their handes they were glad of it, and promiſed him money to doe it, ſo theſe men reioyce when they can haue any occaſion of aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>non law, the iniunctions, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe againſt vs, and both by perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and promiſes, doe incourage others to work our miſchiefe: but they reioyce in their boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, &amp; al ſuch reioycing is euill.<note place="margin">Iames 4.16.</note> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we know to our comfort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> looke as the Lord brought a moſt horrible iudgment vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Tyrus</hi> for triumphing at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fall of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. cap. 26. &amp; 27</note> ſo theſe men ſhall not eſcape the force of the Lords wrath, who being ielous of his honor, cannot abide to ſee his ſeruants abuſed, &amp; his prophets, the apple of his eye made ieſting ſtocks: &amp; as we do admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo we aduiſe all others, to be carefull in this caſe of their
<pb facs="tcp:20078:50"/>
mirthes and triumphes not to reioyce in the wickednes of their handes, and in the ſinnes of others, as it is ſeene nowe a dayes, that there are thoſe, which take a felicitie, and pleaſure to make a man by abundance of drinke looſe the vſe of his ſenſes, laughing at his drunkenes, &amp; reioycing at that, which the ſoules of gods children do moorne for, &amp; they themſelues if there were any feare of God in them ſhould condemne in themſelus: but ſuch is the deſperatenes of this age by reaſon of our corruptions, and want of good diſcipline, that the glory of God lyeth in the duſt, the way of God is euill ſpoken of, and ſin and iniquitie hath gottte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he vpper hand, and trampleth vpon godlines: but leauing the ſorrow and lamentation for the ſame, and prayer either for the redreſſe of all things a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſe, or for the ende and finiſhing of all things, to your Chriſtian ſoules and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, I will proceede with the Apoſtle is the texte, who nowe concludeth with the poore man, and giueth him a ſight of his crowne and glory, and cauſe of ioye, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in a future preferment, or promotion in the wordes, <hi>in that he is exalted.</hi> It is a common vſe not onely of the ſpirit of God in ſcripture, but of vs amongſt our ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:20078:50"/>
alſo in the time of a mans trouble to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comforte vnto him by an argument drawen from the hope of deliuerance, and remedie in the ende. If ye reade the thirtie and one chapter of the prophecie of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> the whole propheſies of <hi>Micha, Nahum, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacuck,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Malachy,</hi> the laſt of the prophets, ye ſhall haue ſufficient proofe, and inſtance of this matter. And in the newe teſtament, yee ſhall light almoſt vpon no leafe, or page, but yee ſhall finde comforts of this qualitie.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.12. Luke 12.32. Luke 23.43 Luke 21.28. Iohn 14.18. Acts. 27.34. 1 Iohn. 2.25.</note> Greate is your rewarde in heauen. It is your fathers pleaſure to giue the kingdome. To day ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe. Lifte vp your heades for your redemption draweth neere. I will not leaue you fatherleſſe, but will come vnto you. There ſhal not an heare fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head of any of you: this is the promiſe that he hath promiſed vnto vs, euen that eternall life w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinite other places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: which courſe is alſo followed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of vs in our conſolations to our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted friends, becauſe we knowe that there can not bee applied to their conſciences, a more ſpeciall matter of comforte, then hope and aſſurance of helpe, and reliefe at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt. The very ſame maner of incourage,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:51"/>
ment, and cheering, <hi>Iames</hi> doth here lay and ſpread before the eyes of the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be contented with his ſtate, to practiſe patience, yea ioy becauſe the time ſhall come wherein, although he bee now in greeuous miſerie, and lye in the duſt, yet hee ſhalbe lifted vp to a ſupreeme degree and heigth of glorie, and ſhalbe made partaker of all the honours, and excellencies of the ſonnes of God: ſo that if there bee any bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or ſiſter among vs, puniſhed, and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any kind of croſſe, and calamitie, whether it be pouertie, weakeneſſe, ſicknes, contempt, diffamation, or perſecution, or whatſoeuer elſe the regarde of the preſent matter, we haue now in hand, may in great meaſure ſtrengthen their feeble armes and ſolace their heauie ſpirites aſſuring them that the ſaid afflictions, ſhall not alwayes continue, &amp; indure vpon them, but ſhall haue not onely an ende but alſo a recompence of ſuch glorie at the laſt, as all the miſeries of this preſent time, are in no reſpect worthy of.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.11.</note> And leaſt any man ſhould miſtruſt the truth of his promiſe, and ſtagger with doubt of the aſſurance, it is with diligence to bee marked, how of purpoſe to take away all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſuch incredulitie, the Apoſtle doth
<pb facs="tcp:20078:51"/>
here vſe not the future but the preſent tenſe, he doth not ſay in that he ſhalbe exalted but in that hee is exalted, as though hee were in preſent fruition already of the ioyes of that kingdome: the like or rather more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all maner of ſpeaking is vſed by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> where to approue the certaintie of the glorie of the faithfull, hee ſpeaketh after the maner of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.13.</note> vſing the time paſt although the benefite be to come, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the time with vs, for he doth not ſay there, that God wil predeſtinate, cal, iuſtifie, and glorifie the faithfull but that hee hath done theſe things already, and that the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfication of the ſaints of God, is as it were paſt &amp; gone, a moſt elegant courſe of words, ratifying, and ſealing vnto the elect their true and vndoubted bleſſednes, &amp; there is no queſtion, but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of God now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; as yet carying about them this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tabernacle, doe notwithſtanding in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences feele as it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taſt &amp; begining of thoſe exceding ioyes, wherof herafter they ſhal haue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercie of God reall, &amp; actuall poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This place doth further ſhew, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proper courſe of aſpiring to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, &amp; prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the felicitie of Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ladder is to aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or
<pb facs="tcp:20078:52"/>
climbe vp by to the gate of perfect glorie: not a dayntie, and delicate life, not a proud, and lordly behauiour, not a quiet ſtate free from all afflictions, and perturbations, but humilitie, lowlines, perſecution, killing, the looſing of the life in this world, theſe are the meanes to ſteppe vp to the ſeat, and ſcepter of true and triumphant happines. The man that is deſirous to come to a vayne of golde, hee muſt digge for it, and diſcend into the bowels of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, without which diſcent he ſhall neuer fulfill his wiſh. <hi>Paul</hi> propoſeth before the <hi>Romans,</hi> and by them before vs, the perſon of Chriſt for an example in this matter,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> who being the ſonne of God by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, firſt ſuffered, and then was glorified: ſo that we being the ſonnes of God by grace, &amp; adoption, and heires anexed with Chriſt, if we purpoſe to be made partakers of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry we muſt firſt be pertakers of his croſſe, &amp; take that courſe for our preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which he did. The regard of which matter may be a ſinguler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful who by reaſon of the afflictions of this life are after a forte battered and throwen down in conſcience, with ſome naturall diſtruſt of the glorie to come: whoſe weake faith is to haue this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their trouble and aduerſities, are the
<pb facs="tcp:20078:52"/>
verie high wayes leading to Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and their miſerie as it were the doore, by which they are to enter and paſſe in, ſo that the feeling of the extremities of this life, is no cauſe why they ſhoulde feare or bee diſcouraged, but rather is as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, and firme obligation, confirming the aſſurance of their future comforts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God in his worde hath made them large promiſes, &amp; therefore as they are hereby to plucke vp their ſpirites, and to comfort their heartes, ſo on the contrary part thoſe men that receiue their conſolations in this life, &amp; cannot abide the ſmart of the leaſt afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhunning it themſelues, doe labour to increaſe the ſame in others, and adde to the bonds of the Saintes, and playe the tyrants ouer the poore, flaying them and ſelling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen for ſhoes, and oppreſſing them with all burdens, they may learne herehence what little cauſe they haue to reioyce in their luſtes, or to take pleaſure in theſe actions, foraſmuch as the time ſhall come, wherein although the poore be made here their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtooles, and bondſlaues, they like Popes riding on their ſhoulders, yet a ſuddayne change, and great alteration, ſhall happen, when the poore man ſhalbe exalted, and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:20078:53"/>
vp to the ſkies, and they ſhalbe taken by the iuſtice of God, and hurled into the depth of hell. And that this is true, hearken what the wiſe man ſaieth concerning the matter, who ſpeaking of the different endes of the wicked, and righteous man, doeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that at the iudgement of al fleſh,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.1.2. &amp;c.</note> the righteous man ſhal ſtande in great boldneſſe before the face of ſuche as haue tormented him, and taken away his labours, but the wicked when they ſee him ſhall bee vexed with a horrible feare, and ſhalbe amazed for his wonderfull deliuerance: and then they ſhall change their minds, and ſigh for griefe, and ſay within themſelues. This is he who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee ſometimes had in deriſion, and in a parable of reproche: we fooles thought his life madneſſe, and his ende without honour, but how is he now counted among the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and his portion is among the Saintes, &amp; therevpon they ſhal breake forth into a condemnation againſt themſelues, &amp; ſay, we haue erred from the way of trueth, &amp; the light of righteouſnes hath not ſhined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and the ſunne of vnderſtanding roſe not vpon vs: we haue wearied our ſelues in the way of wickednes, and deſtruction, and we haue gone thorow dangerous wayes, but we
<pb facs="tcp:20078:53"/>
haue not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the way of the Lord, &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſhall then though too late growe out of conceite with their former vanities of the world, and pleaſures of ſinne, which they inioyed for a ſeaſon, and ſhall crie out, what hath pride profited vs, or what gayne hath the pompe of riches brought vnto vs, for all theſe thinges are paſſed away as a ſhadow and as a poſte that paſſeth by, &amp;c. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if theſe thinges doe not mooue, and cannot woorke the heartes of our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to another conceit of themſelues, and better courſe of life then nowe they holde, I muſt needes pronounce they are made not of fleſh, but of flint and adamant, which beates backe the blow of the hammer, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no impreſſion, but I hope y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and I doe alſo pray to God for them, that a new creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heart may be wrought in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may be touched with a feeling of their own ſinne, &amp; ſenſe of the neceſſities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saintes of God, and may ſo runne the race of this life, that the crowne of righteouſnes ſtored vp for the faithful, &amp; the high degree of exaltatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of the ſonnes of God, ſpoken of here by <hi>Iames,</hi> may bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the mercie of God with them and vs.</p>
               <p>For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helping forward of which matter
<pb facs="tcp:20078:54"/>
in their behalfe, I will now trace forwarde in the ſteppes of the Apoſtle, and goe on with him to the ſecond part, or member of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon heare made, and inſtituted: compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending a ſpecial direction for the rich man, teaching and ſchooling him, as well as the poore man, how he is to behaue himſelfe in his good eſtate, and time of proſperitie, to wit, not to build vpon his wealth, as vpon a rocke or foundation, thinking that there is no qualitie of weakenes, or poſſibilie of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay therein, but rather to conſider the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall incerteinty, and ſlipperines thereof, and vppon that conſideration, to caſt off all his vaine truſt, and fooliſh confidence repoſed in the ſame, and while hee hath his riches in poſſeſſion ſo to vſe it, and diſpoſe of it, as God in his worde hath preſcribed. For ſuche I take to be the meaning of the Apoſtle in the woordes, <hi>Let the riche man reioyce in that hee is made lowe.</hi> That is, let him keepe himſelfe within the compaſſe of his duetie, and thinke that as many times after peace comes warre, and after fayre weather a ſtorme, ſo a great mutation may happen to and vpon his felicitie, whereby it may come to paſſe, that although he be nowe riche, yet he may be made poore: although he be now
<pb facs="tcp:20078:54"/>
mounted aloft,, and riſen vp to the toppe of worldly glorie, yet he may be pluckt downe againe to the earth, and throwen into the duſt of miſerie, as many haue bin before him. And therfore he is to carrie in his heart, this poynt of knowledge, and conſideration, and therewith to be armed in ſuch ſort, as that when this alteration ſhall come, he may bee prepared for it, and goe out as it were to meete it: ſaying with Iob to his wife, ſhall we receiue good things at the hand of God,<note place="margin">Iob 2.10.</note> and not euill alſo? or otherwiſe theſe words may be taken, and that with good probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and ſenſe: to wit, that the rich man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by reaſon of his ſufficiencie &amp; good meaſure of wealth, he be promoted, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to ſome high eſtate, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent calling, yet in his opinion he is to beare a lowe ſayle, and to carry an humble minde ſtill within him, to bee farre from any arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and proud conceit of himſelfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be high in degree, yet to be low in behauiour, in geſture meeke, and in ſpeeche courteous, which thinges are able to winne the generall loue of men, yea of enemies, &amp; in ſuch ſort to apply himſelfe to the practiſe of humilitie in his greateſt honour, as that it may be ſeene that a gentlens of ſpirite, and
<pb facs="tcp:20078:55"/>
lowlines of minde is more regarded of him then the quantitie of his wealth, or the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of his calling: both theſe conſtructions being ſo reaſonable, and ſo agreeable with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe of the Apoſtle, and the duetie of the rich man, wee will ſhortly by the grace of God diſpatch for your comfort, &amp; edifying. I hope you are not ſo ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as not to know, nor ſo frowarde as not to acknowledge the naturall mutabilitie, and vncertaintie that is in this life, and in the poſſeſſion of riches, to day a king, to morowe without a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to day a Queene,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.7.8.</note> no widdowe, ſeeyng no mourning, to morow, a fall, death, ſorow, famine, and burning with fire. <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Booke called the <hi>Preacher,</hi> beeyng written in his latter daies after long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doeth dwell after a ſort vpon this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, proouing largely and ſtrongly, that there is nothing of ſtaye, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance vnder the ſunne, for the very genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doe paſſe and goe away, and all things haue their ende. Who would haue thought reading the beginning of the ſtorie of <hi>Iob,</hi> where it is ſaid that his ſubſtance was ſeuen thouſand ſheepe,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.3.</note> &amp; three thouſand Camels, fiue hundred yoke of oxen, &amp; fiue hundred ſhe Aſſes, his familie verie great, no man in all
<pb facs="tcp:20078:55"/>
the Eaſt part of the world like vnto him, not one amongeſt all the <hi>Arabians, Chaldeans, Idumeans,</hi> and the reſt of the nations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable vnto him for wealth, I ſaye who would haue thought that notwithſtanding all this, hee ſhould by and by reade concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, that in one daye hee had his ſeruauntes ſlaine, his cattell ſtollen, his ſheepe burnt, his children murdered, all that hee had, ſpoyled, deſtroyed, taken away, and nothing left him, yea his very body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo made a ſpectakle of horror, and an image of miſerie, beeing ſmitten with ſore byles from the ſole of his foote to the crowne of his head, and no part remaining whole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him? It is not almoſt credible in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane opinion, that ſo ſodayne a change, ſo miraculous an ouerturne from ſo good a ſtate to ſo vyle a caſe, from ſo muche wealth to ſo much woe, could poſſibly haue happened: but the ſtorie is true, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident is nothing impoſſible, and <hi>Iob</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſed, that as he was borne naked, ſo he ſhould die naked, and that as the Lord had giuen him that wealth, ſo he had alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it away from him at his pleaſure. But what was <hi>Iob,</hi> an Indfidell, and a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate? No ſurely,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.1.</note> an vpright and a iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:20078:56"/>
man, and one that feared God, and eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed euill, ſo ſaith the ſpirite of God expreſly of him, and yet this change from riches to pouertie, and from good to badde fell vpon him, howe much more then are the vngodly ſinners, and vnrighteous men of the world ſubiect to the ſame. Iudgement ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> begins at the houſe of God, if it firſt begin at vs, what ſhall the ende bee of them which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Goſpel of God? and if the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and the ſinner appeare?<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.18.</note> Did Iob, feele the ſuddainneſſe and the waight of an alteration, and ſhall thoſe in whoſe hearte there is no feare towardes God, in whoſe handes there is no innocencie, and in whoſe minde there is no deſire of any good thing, ſhall they eſcape the plague of the ſame? no no, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> affirmeth plainely concerning them, that they ſhalbe conſumed as the fat of Lambes, their proſperitie ſhall paſſe away,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.20.</note> as a clowde, their Bay trees ſhall not alwaies be greene, they ſtande in ſlippery places, the Lorde will caſt them downe into deſolation, they ſhalbe ſuddenly deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.18.</note> periſhed, and horribly conſumed: how many inſtances and examples can I giue you of this matter? but to leaue all,
<pb facs="tcp:20078:56"/>
and to remember one, who can ſufficiently expreſſe, or thorowly deſcribe all the glorie, magnificence, pompe, pleaſure, proſperitie and wealth of <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> the king of <hi>Babel,</hi> who had power ouer all kingdomes,<note place="margin">Iere. 2 6.7.</note> and all nations ſerued him, and did put their neckes vnder his yoke and by reaſon of his conqueſt ouer <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ouer <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iakim</hi> the king of <hi>Iuda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King 2.24.</note> and ouer the houſe of the Lorde, his golde and ſiluer, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was mightily increaſed, and yet for all this, as high as his eſtate was, and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite as his wealth was, you know what iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice happened vnto him: he was cut downe by the watchman, his kingdome was taken from him, and hee from it, and hee became both poore amongſt men,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.30.</note> and miſerable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong beaſtes. This the Lorde our God to whom no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is like is able to do, he maketh poore, and maketh riche, as <hi>Hanna</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Samuel</hi> ſometime did ſing,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.7.</note> hee exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and bringeth lowe, it is as eaſie a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him to make a man a caytiffe, as a king, and a peyſant as a Prince, for health, and ſickneſſe, life and death, proſperitie and beggery they are in his handes, to giue the one for a bleſſing, and to inflict the other for a puniſhment, when, where, and how it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:20078:57"/>
him. How many men are there euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of our own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, who ſomtimes floriſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; braued it out in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt ſort, &amp; who but they? wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting nothing that might ſerue for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of their deſires and the glorie of their pleaſures, ſwimming in ſilkes, abounding with wealth, houſes, grounds, ſheepe, oxen, &amp; many other things, yet nowe they are ſtript into their dublets, and turned as it were to their bag &amp; ſtaff, not ſo ful before as now they are miſerable and emptie: this is the vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinty of humane happines. who therfore but a fooliſh or rather mad man, will truſt this world, &amp; put any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in his wealth, and proceed to ware proud thereof, as though it ſhold for euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with him, nay, ſuppoſe it do ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man a long time, yet although his riches leaue not him, yet he in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end ſhall leaue his riches, &amp; be he as rich as <hi>Croeſus,</hi> or as <hi>Diues</hi> was, yet at the laſt he ſhal iump with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and be as poore as hee. And therfore it is not in vaine that <hi>Paul</hi> in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to <hi>Timothie,</hi> doth of purpoſe touch this particular point of the vncerteinety of carnall wealth.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.</note> Charge them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are riche in this world (ſaith he) that they bee not high minded, &amp; that they truſt not in vncertain ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:20078:57"/>
but in the liuing God. &amp;c. Obſerue the attribute: he doth not ſay, that they truſt not in wicked riches, deceitful riches, or ſuch like words, but in vncertayne riches, which epithete, he doth their vſe as a ſpeciall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſſwade men from the repoſing of any truſt in the ſame: for it is a great foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes to truſt to an vncertayne thing: who will leaue to a broken ſtaffe in leaping ouer a ditch? what mariner wil hazard his ſhip w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cable? what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil build a tower vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a weak fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation? &amp; what diſtreſſed perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil in extremitie relie vpon a ſiccle freinde? now if it be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence of want of wit in a man to do any of theſe things, is it not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like alſo in him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his affiance in riches, being a thing in confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as brittle as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſtaffe, as weak as a rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cable, as totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as a ſandie foundation, as vnconſtant as a wauering friend, as mutable as the winde, and as meltable as the ſnow? let the riche man therefore vpon remembrance of this point if he be carefull of his owne good, caſt of his immoderate deſire of wealth, and vnchriſtian opinion of the ſtrength thereof, &amp; content himſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lawful means in the vſe of his trade, &amp; if God doth bleſſe his labors as he hath promiſed to the righteous man, let
<pb facs="tcp:20078:58"/>
him conuert his ſufficiencie to the inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the kingdome of God, his glorie, the furtherance of his worde, the comfort of the Saintes, and the profite of the Churche of God euery way, not yeelding to the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a fooliſh heart which will carrie a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to oſtentation, pride, and prodigalitie, and other vanities, but in all his actions ſeeking the honour of him, from whome he receiued his bleſſings: let him carefully conſider the vncerteintie for continuance in that he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth, and thereupon while hee hath his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, before the euill dayes doe come, diſpoſe of it according to knowledge and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, leaſt when the yeres of dearth, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie doe approche, then he ſay as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gameſter, and Diceplayer vſually doth, who hauing loſt his mony at one vnthriftie, will then ſweare, and take on, and profeſſe, I would I had rather giuen it to the poore, ſaying ſo when his money being gone is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come another mans, but when hee had it as his owne, he had no ſuch good minde to do it. I my ſelfe haue hearde many, who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time were in good caſe, and ſtate, but nowe are in the contrary, wiſhing that when their abilitie was good, they had done this, and that, to the poore, to the Church of God, to
<pb facs="tcp:20078:58"/>
the Preacher, and to other good vſes, but when they were in their proſperitie they had no ſuch good motion, nor gracious feeling in them. There is no doubt, but that <hi>Diues</hi> when he once felt the torment, &amp; knewe the cauſe therof, he repented ten thouſand times, that hee had not releeued <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his life: but then his repentaunce was too late, and had I wiſt, is alwayes the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eſſentiall propertie of a foole. For a wiſe man will prouide a remedie for a miſchiefe while time ſerues, but a foole when it is too late. Remember therefore the Parable of the talentes, and therein the iudgement of that euill and ſlothful ſeruant,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.26.</note> who not imploying his one talent to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of his maiſter, had the ſame taken from him, &amp; giuen to his diligent fellowe, &amp; himſelfe in the ende, as an vnprofitable hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, throwen into vtter darknes. And ſurely in this reſpect, that place of <hi>Salomon</hi> in his <hi>preacher</hi> is moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, who ſpeaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable mind of the couetous man, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the grace to vſe his riches as he ſhould do,<note place="margin">Eccle. 6.1.2.</note> he doth affirme that he had ſcene an euill vnder the ſun, which was much amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the ſonnes of man, namely, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riches, &amp; treaſures, &amp; honor, &amp; hee
<pb facs="tcp:20078:59"/>
wanteth nothing for his ſoule of all that it deſireth, but God giueth him not power to eate thereof. Which indeede is a plague of plagues, that a man ſhould haue in his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers &amp; cuſtodie, that, by the good vſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee might doe ſingular good in Gods Church, to his glorie, and the ſaluation of many ſoules, &amp; yet doth abuſe his bleſſinges to the maintenance of his pride, bellicheere, wantonnes, luxuriouſnes, couetouſnes, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and other ſinnes, without any regarde of that duetie whereunto the woorde of God doth binde, and direct him. If this thing be well marked, and aduiſedly conſidered of our riche men,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.8.9</note> I doubt not but that by the helpe of God, the ſame good &amp; prudent effect which wrought in the vnrighteous ſteward, vpon the reckoning which his maſter called for at his hands, wil followe in them, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a wiſe, and prouident dealing while they are in office, &amp; a purchaſing of friends by the riches of iniquitie, that when themſelues do want, they may be receiued into euerlaſting habitations: but now, if we take theſe words in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſenſe, namely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the rich man is not to be proud of his wealth, not to boaſt therof, nor to be blowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in any arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit of himſelf therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather to ioyn humility
<pb facs="tcp:20078:59"/>
with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, to be lowly in his own eies, &amp; to bee ſo much the more lowly, by now much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be &amp; is good, ſo is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine profitable, for it teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with what vertue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the reſt, his ſtate muſt be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied &amp; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; with what te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature, he is to mixe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweetnes of his abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of his degree, to be ful, &amp; yet to be as if he were emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rich, &amp; yet as if he were poore, high in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and yet as if he were low in calling, to be of the ſame minde whereof the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle was, as he reportes of himſelf, ſaying,<note place="margin">Philip. 4.12.13.</note> I haue learned in whatſoeuer ſtate I am therwith to be content. I can be abaſed, and I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abound euery where in al things, I am inſtructed, both to be full, and to be hungrie, and to abound, and to haue want, I am able to do al thinges through the helpe of Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth me, as if hee had ſayde in other wordes, when I am on the one ſide pinched with pouerty, loaden with conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts oppreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> miſeries, or howſoeuer afflicted &amp; perſecuted, I am content I diſpaire not, I ſubmit my ſelfe, &amp; refer my caſe to the will, &amp; pleaſure of God, and I doe with patience in mind, &amp; conſtancy in behauiour endure, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the burden of my croſſes. And on the other ſide alſo, when I am out of the perill
<pb facs="tcp:20078:60"/>
of all miſhappes, when my foote hath eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the fowlers net, and my ſoule the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors ſworde, ſo that my life &amp; libertie is in no hazard, or diſtreſſe, &amp; I feele the want of no good thing, then I am not high minded, I waxe not proude, I exalt not my ſelfe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly, &amp; preſumptuouſly, but with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minde, in the feare of God I take and vſe the benefit of his good bleſſings, the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of his loue returning vnto him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of praiſe, &amp; thanks for all things. This is a ſingular diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpirit, &amp; a mirror of mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wiſdom, or rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief ſkil &amp; arte of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God to cary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo vprightly, directly, &amp; equally in al occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as neither by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtorms of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ouerthrowen, nor yet by the ſweete draught of proſperous euentes to bee made drunke, neither to bee diſmayed with the ſharpnes of the Lords diſcipline, and trials, nor yet to ſurfet with the pleaſure of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, but ſo to liue and ſtand in both caſes, as if they were one: &amp; howſoeuer the worlde goeth, or their condition altereth, to bee the ſame maner of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the ſame mind, behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, gouernment, &amp; quality ſtil. Which good and conſtant example in <hi>Paul,</hi> if it were of vs imitated and expreſſed, I ſhould thinke that the ouerflowing riche man woulde
<pb facs="tcp:20078:60"/>
not ſo much forget himſelfe in the time of his felicitie as he doth, liuing in pompe, and ſecuritie without all feare of God, and holy exerciſes: and that the needy poore man alſo, would not ſo often acquaint himſelfe, with vnlawfull actions, practiſed for his violent releife, whereby many times the peace of the countrey is hazarded, and broken, but rather content himſelfe with his meane fortune, and liue within compaſſe of lawe and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, relying vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good prouidence of God, which beeing continually working for ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, will not fayle him if hee faithfully truſt in his mercie. But ye ſe what the drift of my ſpeech is by occaſion of the preſent words, that the riche man if he will reioyce, and be proud of any thing it muſt be of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and not of any vaine confidence in himſelfe, or his wealth, to auoyde the vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious humor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pharaſie, whoſe welth bred pride in his hearte, and the pride of his hearte miniſtred contempt to his lippes,<note place="margin">Luke 18.11.</note> in deſpiſing, and diſdeyning his neighbour the Publican. Which thing is many times a fruite, &amp; conſequence of abundance without ſpeciall moderation, and gouernement. For the Apoſtle affirmeth that the bounteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God leading a man to repentance is
<pb facs="tcp:20078:61"/>
not ſo taken of him but rather conuerted to an abuſe of the Lordes patience, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to the hardening of hearte, and heaping vppe of a treaſure of wrath for himſelfe againſt the day of wrath:<note place="margin">Rom 2.4.5.</note> and in the propheſie of <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Lorde himſelfe makes complaint that whereas by the great meaſure of his bleſſings powred with both his hands vpon his people, he had prouoked them to obedience, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſway of their luſts,<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.7.8</note> and being fed full aſſembled themſelues by companies in the harlots houſes: they roſe vp in the morning like fed horſes, for euery man neyghed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his neighbours wife. The experience of this woful matter we ſee in theſe daies plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie as in a diamond, wherein the good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God which ſhould ſtirre vs vppe to Chriſtian thankefulnes, are ſhamefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, and turned quite as it were againſt the heare, to an engendring, and foſtering of ſinne, and abhomination. As wee are equall with <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in fulnes of bread, ſo in iniquities,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.49.</note> pride, abundance of idlenes, &amp; neglect to ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of the poore and needie. Nay <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and adde to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a third, <hi>Samaria,</hi> theſe neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted halfe of our ſinnes, but we haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb facs="tcp:20078:61"/>
the number of their tranſgreſſions, &amp; haue iuſtified all their workes. And did the Lord in his diſpleaſure make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carry their own ſhame, and confounded them,<note place="margin">Ib. ver. 54.</note> &amp; will he paſſe by vs, &amp; our houſes, &amp; not ſuffer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer to come in? hath he plauged his own citie wherein his name was called vpon, and ſhall we goe free?<note place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> hath he not ſpared the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall branch, and ſhall we that are graftes eſcape the axe, and iudgment? is it not good reaſon, and equitie, that if we commit their ſins, we ſhould alſo feele their ſcourges? for God is not parciall in his iuſtice, neither can any fauour or regard peruert y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of his righteouſneſſe, but as ſure as he liueth we ſhal know the price of our ſins, &amp; feele the ful ſmart of his wrath as they haue done, except we proclayme our faſt, and put on our ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and ſit in aſhes, crying mightelie to the Lord for mercie,<note place="margin">Ionah. 3.5.8 10.</note> and euery man turne from his euil wayes, &amp; from the wickednes of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, then the Lord wil repent him of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath purpoſed againſt vs, &amp; not do it, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he hath ſaid he would do, he wil not do it, otherwiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſe of his bleſſings being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinued, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of our other ſins incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhal procure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſhal neuer be recouered, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrible deſtruction, which ſhall cauſe our names to be abhorred
<pb facs="tcp:20078:62"/>
of the generations to come. Well it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth now onely to ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third &amp; laſt part of our diuiſion, contayning by amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation a reaſon of the former ſpeech of the Apoſtle, wherfore the rich man is not to truſt to his welth, nor to depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of his riches, the reaſon is, becauſe the ſame as <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> is as an Eagle which ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly takes her wings, &amp; flyeth into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, It is a flying thing, a thing ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; chang: no ſurer then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flower of the graſſe, which alwayes periſheth, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away. There are in ſcripture many ſwift thinges to the vncertayne qualities whereof the nature of wealth and riches is likened, and reſembled: as ſometimes to a ſhadow, which of it ſelfe in ſubſtance is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the bare glymſe of the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interpoſed betwixt the ſun &amp; the earth: ſometimes to a poſt, and ſpeedy meſſenger, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in poſt departeth in haſt, either in ſome ſeruice from the prince, or in carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing newes to the court:<note place="margin">Wiſ. 5 9.10.11.12.</note> ſometimes to a ſhip which paſſeth thorow the waues of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the trace whereof being once gone can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found, nor the path thereof ſeene in the floods, ſometimes to a byrde that flyeth in the ayre, and no man can ſee any token of her
<pb facs="tcp:20078:62"/>
flight: ſometimes to an arrow which is ſhot at a marke which deuideth the ayre for a time, but it commeth together againe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, ſo that a man cannot know where it went thorowe, and ſometimes to the duſt which is blowen away by the winde, al theſe things naturally, and liuely expreſſing the hopeleſſe condition of riches, and the truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe proſperitie of this life. But amongſt al other fit, and proper things to this purpoſe, the ſame compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the Apoſtle vſeth in this place, is not the leaſt nor the laſt in conueniencie, and aptnes, making an equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwixt the riche man, &amp; a flower of the graſſe, which although for a time it be very glorious, and beautifull, yet all the glory thereof is weake, and all the beautie thereof vaine, and ſubiect to a ſudden chaunge. And as in this place riches, ſo in other places ſuch things, as are in their prime, and gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are compared with this flower, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt the time of youth, and yonge yeares, is tearmed by the name of the flower of a mans age, becauſe then the body is luſty, the limmes ſtrong, the proportion comely, the blood ſtirring, the wittes freſh, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie quicke, all the powers perfect, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in nature wanting for inwarde and
<pb facs="tcp:20078:63"/>
outward ſufficiencie. But moſt commonly in ſcripture, ſuch things as be ſhort in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and in ſtate tranſitorie, are reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to this flower, as in the booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> that holy, and patient man, entring into a deſcription of the miſerable ſtate and courſe of mans life from his byrth day, to his dying day, affirmeth that man being borne ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth as a flower,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.2.</note> and is cut downe, hee vaniſheth alſo as a ſhadowe, and continueth not. Quickly come, and quickly gone: ſoone ripe, &amp; ſoone rotten as the prouerbe is. The crying voyce in the prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> doth make a difference betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of a graſſe, and of a flower, the one being of longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance,<note place="margin">Eſay 40.6.7</note> though all be but little then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All fleſh is graſſe, but the grace of fleſh, that is the beautie excellencie, wiſdome, and power of fleſh is as the flower of the fieeld, the flower is more orient, and elegant, then the graſſe, but the graſſe is more durable, and permanent then the flower: both are ſubiecte to decay, and corruption, but yet the one droppeth to the earth ſooner then the other. Which thing is to be applied to the wordes of our text, and to be regarded of the riche man with ſome ſpeciall diligence, for as much as himſelfe is heare by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb facs="tcp:20078:63"/>
reſembled, not to the graſſe but to the flower therof, which of the two makes moſt ſpeede to conſumption. The holy Ghoſt by the prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> doth of purpoſe deſcribe a flower, or graſſe, ſhewing what it is, and of what force, and time for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. For hauing ſpoken in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer circumſtances of the Pſalme, of the fragillitie and weakeneſſe, of the breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſhortneſſe of mans life, proouing it to be of no longer perpetuitie, then a day, a floode, a watche, a ſleepe, a thought, and laſt of all a graſſe, hee doth thereupon inlarge that laſt ſimilitude, by expreſſing the ſtate of the ſame graſſe, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (ſayth hee) it floriſheth, and groweth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the euening <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is cut downe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.6.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Which is all one with that further deſcription, which <hi>Iames</hi> makes heare in the next verſe of this chapter, where amplyfying this reaſon which wee haue now in hande, hee ſheweth the maner of the decay of the riche man, by the degrees of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, wherunto the graſſe is ſubiect. For as when the ſunne ariſeth with heate, then the graſſe withereth, and the flower fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away, and the goodlye ſhape of it peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, euen ſo ſhall the rich man wither away
<pb facs="tcp:20078:64"/>
in all his wayes: In which words he tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> general courſe of increaſe, &amp; decreaſe in al vegetatiue &amp; growing things, which as they haue their beginning, ſo they haue alſo their declination, and ende, and cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes continue in one ſtate: ſo in riches there is a beginning, and that ſometimes baſe and ſimple, and as ſmall as the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a roote of a graſſe, or of the ſeede of a flower which is not great in the greateſt. We ſee and knowe amongſt our ſelues, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who now are rich and welthy, and in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie farre beyond many of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who began the world but with a ſmal ſtock, with little or nothing, yet by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, &amp; their own dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, their ſtock is increaſed, their ſtate bettered, and their roome and place nowe reuerend amongſt vs. Which beginning &amp; originall of theirs, I could wiſh many to reuoke, and call backe to memorie, who are now ſo farre gone with pride, and arrogance, by reaſon of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proſperitie, that they forgette the place from whence they came, the parentes from whom they diſcended, the ſimple ſeede from whence the great meaſure of their wealth hath ſpong, and their owne vnworthineſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way without Gods mercie to receiue
<pb facs="tcp:20078:64"/>
any ſuch bleſſinge. Which thing being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, and aduiſedly conſidered, I doubt not, will worke that good effect, which is nowe wanting in thoſe, whom their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath made drunke, and obliuious of their owne progenie, and the graces, and fauours of God towardes them extended: namely thankefulneſſe to God for the ſame, care of his honour, reſpecte of his true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, humilitie, lowlineſſe of minde, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of hearte towards thoſe, who feele nowe the ſharpeneſſe of that want, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, whereunto themſelues in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of many were ſometimes ſubiecte. But by reaſon of the common neglecte of Chriſtian dueties in this caſe, we ſee howe in iuſtice the Lorde doth deale with ſuch maner of men who ſloting vp for a time, as the ſea or flood when it aryſeth, yet at the laſt are brought downe to a low ebbe, and iump in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion with that bare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> figgetree, which receiued a curſe from the mouth of him who neuer bleſſeth vnrighteouſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> and by and by for all his gloriouſe leaues withered, and came to nothing, or with that ſame gourde, which came vp as a ſhadow to the head of <hi>Ionas</hi> for a time, but
<pb facs="tcp:20078:65"/>
beeing ſmitten by a worme preſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dryed vppe,<note place="margin">Ionah. 4.7.10.</note> ſo that as it ſprange in a night, ſo it periſhed in a night. Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our time in this caſe are ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: for the matter is moſt euident, and the men are yet liuing, whoſe ſtates are ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of this iuſtice, and whoſe decay are glaſſes of this declination, their tree of wealth hauing knowen the force of a curſe, and their gourde of pleaſures hauing felt the worme of vengeance, ſo that as their riches already hath, ſo themſelues houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe, according to the wordes of <hi>Iames,</hi> in this place, vaniſh awaye as a flower of the graſſe. Which thing being true I doe not a little maruell, that there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the worlde, who contrary to their owne knowledge (for in this matter they connot pleade ignorance) doe make their wealth their ſupporte, and their treaſure their ſhoote anker, not onely being proude thereof, but that which is an argument of a miraculous vnſenſibleneſſe, doe plant their confidence in the ſame, looking for helpe and deliuerance from their ruſtie and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte gatherings, which ſhall conſume as a ſnayle that melteth, and as the vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:20078:65"/>
fruite of a woman, that hath not ſeene the ſunne. It was a ſpeciall thinge giuen in charge by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie</hi> that hee ſhould inioyne riche men in no caſe to truſt in their riches:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.</note> for hee knewe ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly howe to a riche man a perſwaſion inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truſt and repoſe in his wealth, is moſt plauſible, euen as wee ſee it appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in theſe dayes, by the actions of thoſe men, whom God hath bleſſed with great abundance, who preſuming vppon the ſame, and thinking themſelues able there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to compaſſe any matter, doe applie them ſelues to oppreſſion and tyrranny, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriating or ſkinning the poore man, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging thoſe landes, and poſſeſſions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue no intereſt, but make a claime, and pretenced right, of purpoſe to defraud, and vndoe thoſe, whome they knowe by reaſon of their wantes not able to make their parte good, by continuing the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of lawe againſt them. And many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vile thinges of like nature, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly put in practiſe by them, not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting the ſucceſſe of any matter they take in hande, intending, that if briberie, and corruption, and rewardes, may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb facs="tcp:20078:66"/>
particularly, and peruert the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe courſe of iuſtice they will aſſuredly ſpeed of their purpoſe: this is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſo many bad and odious ſutes are nowe vndertaken and proſecuted, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the foundations, and ſtates of many good men, becauſe the opinion which the vnrighteous man hath of victorie, and preuaylement by his wealth, is a ſpurre in him to tyrranny, ſuppoſing that his golde ſhal beare him out, and the countenance of his money ſhall terrifie as many as reſiſt him. This oppreſſour doth little thinke of the wordes of <hi>Iames</hi> in this place, proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the naturall vncertaynetie of the riche man, and his <hi>Mammon,</hi> or of the mightie fooliſhnes of his heart, or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God entring into his doores, from whoſe handes his money ſhall not ſaue him,<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.19.</note> nor his coyne keepe him in the daye of his wrath. Howe neceſſary then for the time is this doctrine, and that counſell of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophet.<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.10.</note> Truſt not in oppreſſion and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, if riches increaſe ſet not your hearte thereon, and that notable confeſſion of <hi>Iob</hi> alſo for example and direction, whoſe life is a preſident for vs, who ſometimes in
<pb facs="tcp:20078:66"/>
in great vehemencie wiſhed, that his arme might fall from his ſhoulder, and be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the bone,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.24.25.</note> if he had euer made gold his hope, or had ſayde to the wedge of gold thou art my confidence, or reioyced in that his ſubſtance was great, and that his hand had gotten muche. A confeſſion which thouſandes of our dayes cannot make with any trueth, whoſe whole truſt ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the heape of their treaſure, and whole glorie in the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their wealth, hauing the like vayne, and vaineglorious conceite which <hi>Haman</hi> in the Booke of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> who inſtead of acknowledging y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God towards him called his friends together,<note place="margin">Heſter. 5.11.</note> and in the pride of his heart tolde them all the glorie of his riches, and the multitude of his children, and all the things wherein the King had promoted him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But againſt ſuch maner of men the Lorde by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> doeth threaten, to raiſe vp an afflicting nation, from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in of <hi>Hamah,</hi> vnto the wildernes that is a generall deſtruction without the eſcape of anie, becauſe they reioyce in a thing of nought,<note place="margin">Amos 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13.</note> and ſaie haue not wee gotten vs hornes by our owne ſtrength? howe muche
<pb facs="tcp:20078:67"/>
better then were it for vs, and all men to caſt of this peeuiſh confidence in the arme of fleſhe and in the vaniſhing ſhadowe of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall things, and to truſt in him, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, who is the ſhielde, and buckler of the faithfull, the God of all ſtrength and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and able ſufficiently to ſaue thoſe, that relye vppon his goodnes: howe much more profitable for our ſelues, and for our ſoules comfortable were it to put in vſe that ſweet direction of our Sauiour, lay not vp trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for your ſelues vpon earth, where the mothe, and canker doth corrupt, and where theeues doe digge through,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.19.20.</note> and ſteale, but laye vp treaſure for your ſelues in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where neyther the mothe nor canker corrupteth, and where no theeues can digge thorowe to ſteale. Which wordes if they were well conſidered, and diligently exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, woulde appeare to carrie within the compaſſe or bowels of them many good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to diſſwade vs from all miſerable inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of ſcraping together the pelfe of the worlde, and all idolatrous confidences in the ſame. I will not ſtande to diſcourſe at large of thoſe three ſeuerall enemyes to whoſe power the nature of all carnall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:20078:67"/>
is ſubiect, and muſt obey, foraſmuche as there is nothing which a man externally can poſſeſſe, but that in time, either the mothe may frette it, or the canker may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt it, or the theefe may violently breake in and ſurpriſe it, whereby firſt the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the conſumption, and laſt the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſmall ſecuritie of wealth is moſt fully and excellently ſhewed, and withall the huge vanitye of mens heartes condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who ſerue with deuotion, and honour, that tranſitorie traſhe, wherein there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength to continue, nor ſubſtaunce to indure, nor aſſurance to ſtande without decay and loſſe: but this one thing in the woordes maie bee with breuitie obſerued, that our Sauiour doeth there remember vs of the place wherein we liue,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and vſeth the ſame as a reaſon to withdraw our myndes, from the heaping vp of treaſure in the ſame. This earth is not our habitation, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfare: wee are not heere as dwellers for euer, but as ſoiourners for a time, as all our fathers were, wee haue heere no reſt,<note place="margin">Micha. 2.10 Heb. 13.14.</note> nor continuing Citie, but wee muſt ſeeke one to come, wee muſt haue wiues as if wee had none, wee muſt weepe as though
<pb facs="tcp:20078:68"/>
wee wept not, and reioyce as though wee reioyced not, and buye as though wee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed not,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.39.30.</note> and vſe this worlde as though wee vſed it not for the faſhion of this world goeth awaye: and therefore if there were any meaſure of ordinary witte and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in vs, wee woulde not ſo greedily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelues to couetouſneſſe, nor ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally diſpoſe of our ſelues to the loue of the worlde, and worldly thinges as wee doe, beeyng by our owne knowledge ſo natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubiect to a ſhort durance, and ſo conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordayned to an vniuerſal deſtruction, but rather wee woulde reſpect that place, which is immortall, and that treaſure which is incorruptible, and laye vp for our ſelues in ſtore (as the ſpirite ſpeaketh) a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation agaynſt the time to come,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.19.</note> that wee maye obtayne eternall life.<note place="margin">2. Pet 3.10.13.</note> Doe wee not knowe that the Heauens ſhall paſſe awaye with a noyſe, and that the elementes ſhall melt with heate, and that the earth with the woorkes that are therein ſhall bee burnt vp? And if wee doe knowe it, is it not expedient for vs, that wee looke ouer, and beyonde all theſe thinges, and by a holy conuerſation, and faithfull hope, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb facs="tcp:20078:68"/>
newe Heauens, and a newe earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe? Is it not requiſite for vs to bee riſen with Chriſt, and to ſeeke thoſe thinges which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of GOD, that when hee ſhall appeare<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.1.4.</note> and come in iudgement with thouſandes of Angels, wee maye alſo appeare with him in glorie? My beloued brethren, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the Lorde, ſuffer the woordes of exhortation: if there bee any conſolation in Chriſt, if anye comfort of loue, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie felowſhippe of the ſpirite,<note place="margin">Philip. 1.</note> if any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of mercie, looke to your ſelues, and regarde the ſtate of your ſoules: let not the precious death of Chriſt Ieſus bee made without effect in you, grieue not the holy ſpirite of GOD by which you ſhoulde bee ſealed agaynſt the day of redemption,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſet your affections vpon heauenly thinges, and not vppon the thinges of corruption. Let your conuerſation bee without coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, to doe good,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note> and to diſtribute forgette not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is pleaſed, if all theſe thinges be amongeſt you and abounde in you, you cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bee vnfruitefull in the acknowledging
<pb facs="tcp:20078:69"/>
of Chriſt. Nowe the God of peace, that brought agayne from the dead our Lorde Ieſus,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.21.</note> the greate ſhephearde of the ſheepe, through the blood of the euerlaſting coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, make you perfect in all good workes, to doe his wil, working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe for euer, and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:20078:69"/>
            <head>The errors and misprinting of wordes <hi>eſcaped in the preſſe, are here amended,</hi> which otherwiſe might marre the ſenſe, <hi>and hinder the Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Leafe:</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Page:</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Line:</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Error:</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correction.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>rithes</cell>
                     <cell>riches.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>corrupion</cell>
                     <cell>corruption.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>gteater</cell>
                     <cell>greater.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>exceeded</cell>
                     <cell>exceede.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>theſe</cell>
                     <cell>thoſe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>in in</cell>
                     <cell>in</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>beefore</cell>
                     <cell>beeing.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>approueth</cell>
                     <cell>appeareth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>which</cell>
                     <cell>with.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>wee</cell>
                     <cell>were</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>externall</cell>
                     <cell>eternall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>his</cell>
                     <cell>this.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>riches ches</cell>
                     <cell>riches.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>for</cell>
                     <cell>ſo.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>hee</cell>
                     <cell>the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>forte</cell>
                     <cell>ſorte.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>ſaide</cell>
                     <cell>ſaie.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>flying</cell>
                     <cell>flitting.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>ſponge</cell>
                     <cell>ſprang.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>bare</cell>
                     <cell>barren.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>lb.</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>ground</cell>
                     <cell>gourde.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>hope</cell>
                     <cell>heape.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London at the three Cranes in the Vintree <hi>by Thomas Dawſon for</hi> Thomas Butter. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
